<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Londons vvarning, by Ierusalem A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse on Mid-Lent Sunday last. By Francis White, Mr. of Arts, and sometime of Magdalene Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>White, Francis, b. 1588 or 9.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15086</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119902</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855108</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855108</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20580</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15086)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20580)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1225:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Londons vvarning, by Ierusalem A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse on Mid-Lent Sunday last. By Francis White, Mr. of Arts, and sometime of Magdalene Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>White, Francis, b. 1588 or 9.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslowe, for Richard Flemming: and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the three Flower-de-Luces, in Saint Pauls Alley, neere Saint Gregories Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
                  <note>Title page mutilated; pages 9-10 stained. Beginning - page 25 from British Library copy spliced at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20580:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LONDONS VVARNING, BY <hi>JERVSALEM.</hi> A SERMON PREACHED AT PAVLS CROSSE ON MID-Lent Sunday laſt.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis White,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of Arts, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time of <hi>Magdalene</hi> Colledge in <hi>OXFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Devt. 32.29</bibl>
               <p>Oh that they were wiſe, then they would understand this: they would conſider their latter end.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Purſlowe,</hi> for <hi>Richard Flemming:</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Signe of the three <hi>Flower-de-L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Alley, neere Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> Church. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:20580:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>Vox index animi: Vox index eſto libelli:</l>
            <l>Vox clamans titulum: Signat amans animum.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20580:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, AND RELIGIOVS <hi>Lady:</hi> MARY <hi>Lady</hi> HVNSDEN: <hi>as</hi> alſo to her truely Noble, and moſt vertuous Sonne, <hi>Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Hunſden:</hi> the bleſſing of <hi>Heauen and earth be multiplyed.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Reſuming on your fauours, I am emboldned to preſent you with the firſtlings of my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours, who may beſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge them, beeing the firſt who gaue life and breath in your incouragements to theſe my intendements. For neuer had I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged my ſelfe ſo farre in theſe more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique imployments, but had contented my ſelfe in an obſcure retire on my rurall Charge; but that the experiments of your fauour did for a while dictate another courſe vnto me: which ſince good conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations
<pb facs="tcp:20580:3"/>haue altered; it being aſwell your religious deſire, as my care, to feede mine owne flocke at home, though but a very little one, beeing in a place altogether diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopled, rather then to intend anothers Charge abroad: I had ſometime thought the deſolatenes of the place had been ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient priuiledge for abſence: but I finde it otherwiſe: many being ready to find fault, as <hi>Eliab</hi> did with <hi>Dauid</hi> for leauing,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.28.</note> though but a few Sheepe in the Wilderneſſe. And therefore, to giue offence to none, I will ſeeke no farther excuſes for my abſence, but returne vnto mine owne: and ſith my abſence can no longer ſuffer mee to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that ſeruice to your Honors which I could wiſh: I ſhall leaue this ſmall Preſent with you, as a pledge of that duty &amp; ſeruice which I owe: making vp in my dayly prayers to God for your Honors, what ſhal bee wanting in the performances of my ſeruice to you: deſiring the God of Heauen to bleſſe your Honors with the bleſſings of this life, and bleſſednes of a better.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt deuoted Chaplaine: <hi>FRANCIS WHITE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20580:3"/>
            <head>TO THE WORTHY SOCIETIES OF CITIZENS in this famous Citie of LONDON, in eſpeciall to his louing friends of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Sepulchres.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat was ſometime preached to the eare, is now preſented to the eye: and the rather this, becauſe the more may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, if any thing there be, which any wayes may concerne the Peace of our Hieruſalem. Nothing there is at all, which may deſerue the Printing: but if any thing there be, which any wayes may auaile the ſoules good; the Lord Print that in the Heart: which is all I ayme at, or can deſire. I hope it will be offence to none, but to ſuch onely who put the gaine of Deceit into a broken Bagge (for whom I paſſe not) that our Prophets In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiue againſt the ſcant meaſure, wicked Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances,
<pb facs="tcp:20580:4"/>and the bagge of deceitfull weights, is renued in theſe times, and ſome of the Citie cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners not exempted from it: which Diſcipline in time (no doubt) will redreſse and purge; That glorious things may euer bee ſpoken of thee,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>87.</hi>
               </note> thou Citie of God: and the Lord may ſtill loue the habitations of <hi>Iacob,</hi> where his Name is called vpon, and his will obſerued. Thus ſeeke wee ſtill the peace of our Hieruſalem, breaking off our ſinnes by repentance, being at peace with God; that the God of peace and loue, may eſtabliſh for euer peace within our Walles, and ſet plenty within our Palaces, to his glory, and the comfort of vs all in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all Chriſtian Offices, and ſeruices of loue, FRANCIS WHITE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20580:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>LONDONS WARNING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MICAH. 6.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lords voice cryeth vnto the Citie, and the man of wiſedome ſhall ſee thy name: heare ye the rod, and who hath appointed it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aieſtie in this Chapter ſeemes to parly euen with miſery: God par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies with man; and that the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of a gracious God, with an vnthankfull people, may appeare moſt iuſt, Heauen and earth, the dumbe creatures of God, which in the nineteeneth Pſalme are ſtiled the ſilent Preachers of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; mercy, vnto man, are heere cited to be eare-witneſſes of mans vnthankfulnes vnto God. For in the ſecond verſe, <hi>Heare ye, O Mountaines, and yee mightie foundations of the earth, the Lords quarrell againſt his people.</hi> The witneſſes thus produc't, Rockes and Mountaines, to conuince the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mans heart, and height of rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his God. God, he begins his plea, and ſhewes the ancient euidences of his loue: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>O my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20580:5"/>people,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>4</label> ſaith God, <hi>what haue I done vnto thee, or wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in haue I grieued thee? teſtifie againſt me.</hi> Is it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I brought thee out of Egypt, and redeemed thee out of the houſe of ſeruants, and led thee like a flocke, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>5</label> by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron?</hi> Is it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I turned <hi>Balaams</hi> curſe into a bleſſing vnto you? Is it, becauſe from Shittim vnto Gilgal, nay, from Egypt, vnto Canaan, I made knowne to you, my mercy, my power to your enemies? Is it this that ye lift vp the heele againſt mee? Is it this my kindnes, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> makes you thus vnkind vnto me? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, O my people, theſe great mercies of your Sauiour, and ſo acknowledge the righteouſnes of the Lord. This is Gods gracious plea with his vnthankefull people, which did ſo wound and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſh their guiltie conſcience, that they cry out in the ſixt verſe: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>7</label> 
               <hi>In quo occurram?</hi> wherewith ſhall I come before the Lord? And now God, he ſhall haue burnt offerings; hee ſhall haue thouſands of Rammes; nay, ten thouſand Riuers of Oyle; nay, their firſt-borne child, the fruit of their body, for the ſinne of their ſoule, And all this now if the Lord he will be but pleaſed. But this God, well he knowes, to be but cruſted obedience; much like vnto a wound, which deceitfull skill gathers to a skin, while within 'tis putred and rankles to the bone: For ſo this ſeeming obedience, it doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten palliate the rancour and malice of an euill heart: and therefore, <hi>indicauit tibi, O homo,</hi> God he ſhews thee, O man, in the 8. Verſe, <hi>what is good, and what the Lord requireth of thee: Surely, to doe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20580:5"/>iuſtly, and to loue mercy, and to walke humbly with thy God,</hi> which is the full ſumme of the Decalogue, and the whole dutie of Man. And all burnt-offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, thouſands of Riuers of Oyle, the fruit of the body, for the ſinne of the ſoule, they are all but <hi>ſplendida peccata,</hi> they are but glittering ſinnes, if this be wanting, to doe iuſtly man with man, which is the one halſe dutie of man, and to walke hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with thy God, which is the other. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being the very life and ſoule of our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, without which our obedience, like a dead carkaſe, ſtinkes in the noſtrils of the Lord, that you may all of you take notice of it, and not content your ſelues with imperfect Comma's of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to doe ſome part of that which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth: nor yet with imperfect Colons of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, to doe the one halfe of that which God commandeth: but that you may ſtill endeuour to conclude all your actions with full Points of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to doe all which God commandeth; not mans, but the Lords voice cryeth this in your eares; For <hi>the Lords voice cryeth vnto the Citie, and the man of wiſedome ſhall ſee thy name. Heare ye the Rod, and who hath happainted it.</hi> Which Text of holy Scripture ſeemes to haue in it the compoſure of a Syllogiſme. The Maior Propoſition in theſe words: <hi>The Lords voice cryeth vnto the Citie.</hi> The Minor in theſe words: <hi>The man of wiſe dowe ſhall ſee thy name:</hi> that is, ſhall ſee and conſider the glory of Gods name, his Maieſtie, and his power, and ſo with reuerence attend vnto his voice. The illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20580:6"/>or Concluſion, by way of exhortation, in theſe words: <hi>Heare ye therefore the Rod:</hi> He that is a man of wiſedome amongſt you, let him lend his eares and heart to heare of a Rod which the voice denounceth; vnleſſe ye turne from the euill of your waies: which God hath appointed moſt certainely to bring vpon you; vnleſſe you preuent his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, with your penitence. In the Maior conſider we,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Cuius hac vox,</hi> whoſe voice this is: it is the Lords voice.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Qualis,</hi> what manner of voice it is: It is a crying voice: <hi>The Lords voice cryeth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The <hi>vbi,</hi> the place where it cryeth; and that is the Citie. <hi>The Lords voice cryeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Citie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In the Minor conſider we:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Quibus,</hi> to whom this voice is directed: to men of wiſedome: <hi>The man of wiſedome ſhall ſee thy name.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The reaſon why the voice is directed onely vnto ſuch: and that is, becauſe they ſee Gods name: they haue an awefull feare and reuerence of the great Maieſtie of God, which tunes their eares and hearts, and makes them tuneable to this voice, to attend with reuernce vnto the voice of ſo high a Maieſtie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:20580:6"/>
            <p> In the Concluſion, conſider we:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid clamat:</hi> What the voice cryeth: It tels vs louingly of a Rod from God: <hi>Heare yee the Rod, and who hath appointed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be the parts of this Text, and you haue the Lords voice in the front of it, and the Lords Rodde, in the concluſion or ſhutting vp of it; to ſhew how that they who will not heare the Lords Voice at the firſt, ſhall be ſure to feele his Rod at the laſt. Let vs therefore in the firſt place attend vnto that, which is firſt propoſed: which is,<note place="margin">Pſal. 29.</note> 
               <hi>Vox Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houae,</hi> the Lords voice. The Lords voice (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi>) is a mighty voice, it makes Heauen and earth to ſhake: And ſo terrible is this voice to fleſh and bloud, that in the 20. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>19</label> the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> cry out vnto <hi>Moſes: Speake thou with vs, and we will heare: but let not God ſpeake with vs, leſt we die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam,</hi> before his fall, could well enough endure to heare the voice of God; but no ſooner had hee tranſgreſt, but as you reade, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 3. when hee heares the voice of God, he is afraid: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>10</label> 
               <hi>I heard thy voice in the Garden, and was afraid.</hi> And this is the condition of vs all, ſince the fall of our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, we are ſo afraid to heare the voice of God, that we cry out with the Iſraelites: <hi>Let man ſpeake with vs, and wee will heare: but let not God ſpeake with vs, leſt we die.</hi> And therefore, though in my Text mention be made of the Lords voice, this voice, it is not the Lords voice, which ye are afraid
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20580:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>to heare, leſt ye dye: But the Lords Prophet is the Lords voice in this place, which if ye heare not, ye die: &amp; this it is no new thing, for the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to bee ſtiled the Lords voice. For in the firſt Chapter of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpel, there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the word, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the voice Chriſt, he is the Word: Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> Chriſts Herauld, hee is the voice to publiſh and proclaime this word. So that Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> he was the Lords voice to proclaime vnto the Iewes <hi>verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dominum,</hi> the Word which is God. And our Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> in this place, he is the Lords voice to publiſh vnto the Iewes, <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum Domini,</hi> the Word of God, the Word of the Lord. Now it is not ſaid to be the Prophets voice which publiſhes the meſſage, but the Lords voice; becauſe the people ſhould attend with reuerence to the Prophets, Gods Miniſters voice, euen as they would to the Lords owne voice: ſith Gods Meſſenger, he is no other but <hi>vox Iehouae,</hi> the Lords voice. Man indeed is the voice, becauſe wee are confounded when God himſelfe doth ſpeake: but not mans, but the Lords is the voice; becauſe though man vtter them, yet wee ſhould take the words as ſpoken from God, who elſe would ſpeake the words vnto vs himſelfe, but that our infirmitie cannot away with the Maieſty of the Speaker, who therefore makes man the voice, becauſe man may well away to heare what man doth ſpeake: and therefore though he make man the voice, yet will not haue the voice acknowledged to bee mans voice, but the Lords voice; becauſe wee ſhould
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20580:7"/>attend to what is ſpoken, as ſpoken from God, and not from man, who is onely the Lords voice.</p>
            <p>And thus now you ſee who is the Lords voice in this place: See we withall what inſtructions we haue by this: why, firſt we haue Gods mercy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to vs, who vouchſafes to ſend a voice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a rodde: a voice to premoniſh, before a rod to puniſh: Secondly, wee haue Gods Miniſters dutie ſet before vs, in that he is <hi>vox,</hi> in that he muſt be a voice. Thirdly and laſtly, we ſee Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters dignitie, in that hee is <hi>vox Iehouae,</hi> the Lords voice. For the firſt, Gods mercy, in that he ſends a voice to premoniſh, before a rodde to puniſh. And this mercy of God, it is euery where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto vs in holy Writ; from the <hi>Alpha,</hi> to the <hi>Omega;</hi> from the beginning, to the end. The firſt man <hi>Adam,</hi> no ſooner had hee loſt himſelfe, ſtraying in forbidden pathes from his Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; but the voice of mercy ſeekes him out in the third of <hi>Geneſis: Vbies?</hi> Adam, <hi>where art thou?</hi> Wicked <hi>Cain,</hi> he murthers a righteous <hi>Abel:</hi> and the voice of mercy ſtraight vpon the murther cals vpon him, to ſtrike him with remorſe for his ſinne, <hi>Vbi eſt?</hi> VVhere is thy Brother <hi>Abel?</hi> Alas,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> what haſt thou done, that thy Brothers bloud cryes in mine eares for vengeance? The old world,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.19, 20.</note> though now euen drowned with the ouerflowings of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe, yet, it periſhed not by the floud, but it had firſt a voice to admoniſh it: righteous <hi>Noah</hi> was ſent vnto it a preacher of righteouſnes. <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueh</hi> that great Citie, God, he had purpoſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20580:8"/>it, for the Cry of their ſinne, which came vp to Heauen: but a voice is firſt ſent vnto them; <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> like a Doue is ſent from before Gods Mercy-Seat, with the Oliue Branch of Peace in his mouth,<note place="margin">Ionah 1.</note> to flie to <hi>Nineueh</hi> with the ſiluer wings of mercy, offering them mercy, if they doe repent. And to come nigher home. Heere in my Text, you ſee <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> rebellious <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> a Citie ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull to her God; yet ſhe hath a voice firſt ſent vnto her, the voice of mercy, to make her heare the rodde, before the hand of iuſtice is vpon her, to make her feele the rodde. And as the Citie <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> was vouchſafed this voice of Mercy, to winne her home by repentance to her God: So this our <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> this Citie of ours, a Citie as vnkind to God, as euer was <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> yet hath it voices vpon voices ſent vnto it; it is full of voices: &amp; theſe voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with that voice of a Crier in the third of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> forewarne vs to flee from the wrath to come. Some of theſe voices Cry vnto the Citie, to take heed how ſhe harbours Drunkards, leſt the Land ſpue out her Inhabitants, as a lothſome burthen to her ſtomacke. Some of theſe voices Cry vnto the Citie, to take heed how ſhe deale with Pride, leſt pride, like <hi>Samſon,</hi> carrie away the gates of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vpon her back, and betray the ſtrength of the Citie, whil'ſt with her ouer-curious cloathing ſhe leaues the Citie bare, and like an Ague, hauing faſhious for fits, ſhakes the Common-wealth, whilſt ſhee makes her wealth too common for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations, dearely buying at their hands, their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20580:8"/>ſtrange faſhions, and new deuices, till at laſt Pride get a trip and (if preuention ſtep not in) lay the Cities honour in the duſt. Some againe of theſe Voyces Cry vnto the Citie to take heed ſhee bee not too ſecure, for the Diuel is like the Vſurer, all is well with him, ſo long as he ſees ſecurity.</p>
            <p>Thus the Voyces, you ſee, they diſcharge like ſo many Warning-pieces vpon you, euen from God, to forewarne you to flee from the wrath to come: now if yee will not heare this voyce of Mercie, but like wel-fed Horſes will fetch your full careeres in ſinne, and ſeeme to ſpurne againſt the Decree of Heauen, diſdaining to humble your ſelues in duſt and aſhes, and to come before God, in Faſting, Teares, and Prayer; if the rod of God, on the ſudden ſmite any one,<note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> with <hi>Belſhazzer</hi> quaffing in his Cups; or priding it with <hi>Iezabel;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 9.</note> or promiſing ſecurity to himſelfe with <hi>Diues:</hi> let him not blame GOD for his ſeuerity;<note place="margin">Luke 12.</note> for God ſent Voyces vpon Voyces to recall him, but he would not bee recalled: and therefore let him blame his owne ſtupid ſecuritie, who would not bee wonne with the voyce of Mercie, vntill he feele the ſtroke of Iuſtice. For vs (Beloued) ſith God thus in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſtill vouchſafes a Voyce to premoniſh, before a Rod to puniſh; let vs heare and obey the Voyce of Mercie, that ſo wee may preuent the ſtroke of Iuſtice: for to bee all eare and heart, to heare and obey, is the Peoples dutie, as to bee all Voyce and Heart, to exhort and obey is the Miniſters dutie, which wee haue in the ſecond place commended
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20580:9"/>vnto vs; in that, Gods Miniſter, he is <hi>vox,</hi> in that he is a voice. Gods Miniſter he muſt be a voice. For in the 28. of <hi>Exodus, verſe</hi> 35. wee reade, that <hi>Aarons</hi> ſound muſt be heard when he goeth into the Holy place, to miniſter before the Lord, that he dye not. Wherevpon ſaith venerable <hi>Beda,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Sacerdos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grediens, vel e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grediens, moritur ſi de eo ſonitus non audiatur, quia iram contra ſe occulti Iudicis exigit, ſi ſine prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicationis ſonitu incedit. <hi>Beda</hi> de veſt. Sacerd. <hi>1. Cor. 9.16. Mar. 16.15.</hi>
               </note> The Prieſt comming to miniſter before the Lord, he dyes for it, if his ſound be not heard: and the Miniſter of the Goſpell, hee ſtands guilty of death, if hee take vpon him to miniſter before the Lord, and haue not his ſound heard in the ſincere preaching of the Goſpell. Gods Miniſter then needs muſt he be a voice. For wo vnto him if he be not a voice: <hi>Woe vnto me</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>if I preach not the Goſpell;</hi> for their Commiſſion is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Preach the Goſpell. This then commends the neceſſitie of preaching, againſt the common voice of the world, which holds a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe againſt the Schoole of Chriſt; that the more preaching, the leſſe practifing; and, Neuer were there more golden times, then when there was leſſe voycing it in the Pulpit, and more mumming and maſſing it at the Altar: This is a ſtrange world, when the more we are taught to doe, the leſſe we doe; and when mens eares are like the thin eares of Come, which <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaw in a dreame, in the 41. of <hi>Geneſis;</hi> the thinne eares deuoured the full eares: For ſo our thinne eares, which ſcarce heard good inſtruction in time of Popery, deuoure our full eares, which now in the light of the Goſpell are dayly fild with good inſtructions: for when
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20580:9"/>we heard little, the boaſt is, we did much; and now we heare much, the cry is, wee doe iuſt nothing at all. And therefore if God ſhould deale with vs in iuſtice, and not in mercy, rather then hee would ſuffer his voice thus to be wronged, to be thought the occaſion of our ſeldome practice, and ſlacke performance, he would quite take his Voices from vs, and ſith we will not be content to be brought to heauen, by the direction of his Voice, ſuffer vs to goe to hell, by the ſuggeſtion of the Diuell, but God pities our infirmitie: and though we (ſuch is the weakenes &amp; errour of our iudgement) think the voice cry too too often, yet God (ſuch is the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and dulnes of our hearts) thinkes the voice neuer to cry often enough. And therefore in the 58. of <hi>Iſai. verſe</hi> 1. ſaith God vnto his Voice, vnto his Prophet; <hi>Cry, Cry alowd, Spare not, but lift vp thy voice like a Trumpet, and ſhew my people their tranſgreſsion, and to the houſe of</hi> Iacob <hi>their ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now doth the voice of God ſay, <hi>Cry;</hi> the voice of man, needs muſt it cry, what the voice of God would haue it cry. And therefore all that be Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, let them not ſpare to cry, while they haue a voice to cry, let the world regard their often cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it pleaſe.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe, who haue the calling of Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who are called to be <hi>Vocales,</hi> but proue <hi>muti:</hi> who are called to be vocall, but proue mute: it were to be wiſhed, they would a little ſtraine their voice, to ſpeake ſomewhat in Gods cauſe; that if not their voice, yet at leaſtwiſe their ſound might
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20580:10"/>be heard in Gods Temple, as <hi>Aarons</hi> was, whilſt, though themſelues be ſlow of Speech, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.</note> yet they procure ſome <hi>Aaron</hi> to bee their mouth, their ſound vnto the people that they die not, if their ſound bee not heard, and the peoples bloud which periſh by their default, bee not one day required at their hands.</p>
            <p>Now as this, it is for the Miniſters duty, that he is a voice; ſo is it alſo for his dignitie, that he is <hi>vox Iehouae,</hi> the Lords voice: and this that hee is the Lords voice, it firſt reflects in a <hi>memento,</hi> to the Miniſter himſelfe; and then ſecondly, to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. For the Miniſter himſelfe, in that hee is the Lords voice, it teaches him integritie, and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
            <p>And firſt, integritie: for he, whom the God of Heauen makes choiſe of, to be his voice, need had he be,<note place="margin">Luke 1.</note> as was <hi>Zacharias</hi> the Prieſt, a man iuſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, walking without reproofe. Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter then, he muſt not be a bare voice; but he muſt be, as was Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a voice, he muſt be more then a voice, and his heart muſt vtter workes of piety, when his tongue ſpeakes words of pietie; his hands muſt deale workes of charitie, when his tongue deliuers words of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: nay, more then this, his modeſt cloathing, like <hi>Iohns</hi> garment of Camels hayre;<note place="margin">Math. 3.</note> this muſt bee a voice, &amp; preach againſt the faſhions of the times. His temperate dyet, like <hi>Iohns</hi> meat of Locuſts, and wilde Honey; this muſt be a voice, and preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Ryot of our times: and thus muſt he be,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20580:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>not ſo much a ſpeaking, as a walking voice; for he muſt approue himſelfe to God, as did Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 5.</note> not onely a ſhining, but a burning light: not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſhining light, to lighten the dimme Candle of our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, &amp; to make vs to know God: but a burning light to inflame the fire of our loue, and to make vs to loue God. He muſt be a preaching voice whereſoeuer hee goes; as in the Temple, preaching words of Pietie; ſo out of the Temple, preaching works of pietie, that the ſinceritie of his workes, may giue countenance to the veritie of his words. And this was ſignified in <hi>Aarons</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; when as we reade in the 28. of <hi>Exodus, verſe</hi> 34. vpon the skirts of <hi>Aarons</hi> cloathing, there was a golden Bell and a Pomegranate: a Bell, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Gods Miniſter, he muſt be a ſounding, a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching voice: a golden Bell, to ſignifie the doctrine which he preaches, muſt be ſincere and pure; pure as the gold tried ſeuen times in the fire: and with this golden Bel is ioined a Pomegranate, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Gods Miniſter: he muſt not onely be a Bell to ſound out the Goſpell; nor onely a golden Bell, ſound in the ſincere preaching of the Goſpel; but he muſt be alſo, a Pomegranat: as the Pomegranat is full of pleaſant kernels, ſo muſt Gods Miniſter abound alwayes in the worke of the Lord; be full of good workes: <hi>vt omnia quae loquitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beda de veſt. Sacerd.</note> 
               <hi>bonis confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentur operibus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Beda:</hi> That the confirmation of his doctrine, may be the conformation of his life vnto his Doctrine. Now if euer any Church in the world had in it this ring of golden Bels, it is the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20580:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Church of <hi>England</hi> at this day. The church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath indeed a ring of Bels, but they be Tinne, they be Lattine Bels, &amp; the Latine, often broken Latine too, which makes the ring ſo much the worſe. For the Prieſts of <hi>Rome</hi> beat ſo altogether vpon Latine, in the ſeruices of their Church, that moſt of them (ſuch is the ignorance of their Maſſe-Prieſts) doe often breake it: whereas our ring, it is altogether of golden Bels, ſound and ſincere Preachers of the Goſpell; delightfull for their pleaſant ſound, and as delightfull for their pleaſant ſauour. For as they be golden Bels, for the purity of their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine; ſo be they alſo Pomegranats, for their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous life. Now, if it ſo ſometime chance to hap you meet with a golden Bel, without a Pomgranat; a good Preacher for his Doctrine, but not ſo good for his life; neuer the worſe miſlike the ring, but heare his doctrine, and beare with his life. For well ſaith a good Father;<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Mat. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si benè vixerint:</hi> The Miniſters, if they liue well, the benefit is their own; <hi>Si benè docuerint,</hi> if they teach well, the benefit is yours; <hi>accipite igitur quod veſtrum eſt, nolite diſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere quod alienum eſt:</hi> receiue therefore, and skan their Doctrine, for that belongs to you: meddle not to skanne their life, for that belongs to God; for they are the Lords Voices, and they ſtand or fall vnto their owne Maſter: but (God be thanked) neuer were the Lords voices, theſe golden Bels, better tuned, for life and doctrine, then at this day: the Lord ſo continue them, who firſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaf't them to be his Voices, that theſe golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Saint-Bels
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20580:11"/>may ring all in, may winne all miſ-led Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to ioyne with vs in our holy profeſſion, while their <hi>light ſo ſhines before men, that men ſeeing their good workes, glorifie their Father, which is in Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the ſecond place, as the Miniſter ſees his glory in this, that he is Gods Voice, ſo that he may not be proud of this, that he is ſo highly dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to be the Lords voice, he muſt withall learne this point of humilitie, how that hee is but the voice, the Word, God puts it into his mouth what he ſhall fay, and he is but the Voice to publiſh it. And this we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed vnto vs out of the 40. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> where at the ſixt <hi>verſe,</hi> ſaith God vnto the Prophet, <hi>Cry.</hi> Now the Prophet thus approued, to be Gods Voice to cry, he awaits his meſſage from God, and in humilitie hee replyes to God, <hi>Quid clamabo?</hi> What ſhall I cry? Now God, he puts his word into his Prophets mouth, and bids him cry, <hi>All fleſh is graſſe, and the grace thereof is as the flower of the field.</hi> So that by this you ſee, though the Prophet be the Voice to publiſh the meſſage, yet the Word, God puts it into his mouth what hee ſhall ſay. And therefore the Prophets beeing to deliuer their meſſage from God, they ſhew their warrant, and ſtill begin with this, <hi>Verbum Iehouae,</hi> the word of the Lord. For ſo begins our Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> this his Prophecie,<note place="margin">Chap. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Word of the Lord that came vnto</hi> Micah: as if <hi>Micah,</hi> and all other the Prophets, were but ſo many Voices, ſtill ready at hand, awaiting and expecting to receiue the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20580:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Word of the Lord, whenſoeuer it came vnto them for to publiſh it.</p>
            <p>Now, this being ſo, that Gods Miniſter, he is but the voice; the Word, God puts it into his mouth what hee ſhall ſay. Why then firſt, let no Meſſenger of the moſt High, no Miniſter of the Goſpell, be any whit proud, or lifted vp with this, though hee farre ſurpaſſe all other in the gifts of the Spirit: for alas, he, who thinkes himſelfe the beſt, and beſt furniſhed for the Miniſterie, hee is but the Lords Voice; and not a word, not a tittle can he vtter of himſelfe, but onely the Word which the Lord God putteth into his mouth: euen <hi>Balaam</hi> in the 22. of <hi>Numbers</hi> tels him as much; where hee tels vs, no not for a houſe full of gold and ſiluer, he can ſpeake a word good or bad, but onely the Word, which GOD putteth into his mouth to ſpeake; that, and no other can he ſpeake. So that euery Miniſter of God, he muſt in humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie acknowledge and confeſſe, what <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> before him ſtood not vpon to vtter,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.23.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I am but the voice of him that cryeth, of God that ſpeaketh by mee: For that which was matter of pride in <hi>Herod,</hi> to heare the acclamation of the people, The Voice of God, and not of Man, muſt be matter of humilitie in the Miniſters of God, when they heare (The Voice of God, and not of Man) ſith they be but Gods Voices,<note place="margin">Acts 12.22.</note> &amp; the Word, God puts it into their mouth what they ſhall ſay. And therefore in the ſecond place, in that Gods Miniſter he is but the Lords Voice, the Word it is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20580:12"/>Gods Word, and hee is but the Voice to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it. This condemnes the great folly of the world which is ſo ready to taxe the Miniſter. And if his Doctrine, like the Arrow ſhot at per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture, which ſmote wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> betweene the ioynts, light vpon ſome <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 22.34.</note> ſome vngodly man entring thorow, as the Word of GOD is liuely, and mighty in operation,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding aſunder of the ſoule, the Spirit, the ioynts and marrow: This wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 22.8.</note> this vngodly man, he will hate the Lords <hi>Michaiah</hi> for this, hee will hate the Lords Voice for this; becauſe he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, he preaches not good, but as he conceitsit euil vnto him; whereas ſond man, he conſiders not with himſelf, how that the word it is Gods Word, and the Miniſter, he is but the Lords Voice to publiſh it, and the Voice neither can it vtter good or bad, but what the Lord God putteth into the mouth to ſay, as <hi>Micaiah</hi> told the Meſſenger of <hi>Ahab,</hi> who entiſed him to accord with the falſe prophets, and to bring in his <hi>omnia bene</hi> with the reſt: <hi>Surely</hi> (ſaith <hi>Micaiah</hi>) <hi>as the Lord liueth, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Lord ſaith vnto me, be it good, or be it bad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>that, and no other can I ſpeake.</hi> And therefore as we blame not the Bow, if the Arrow hit vs, but rather the hand which directed toward vs: ſo let not men ſtorme againſt the Voice, which carries but the word vnto our eares. But what then, ſhall we ſtorme againſt the hand of God which aymes the Word directly vnto vs? Why, ſtorme we; if we will: but <hi>Dauid</hi> tels vs in his ſecond Pſalme, wee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20580:13"/>rage and murmure but in vaine: &amp; if our rage be not the ſooner ouer, God ſhal vex vs in his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and breake theſe veſſels of Clay; theſe bodies of ours like a Potters Veſſell: be we wiſe therefore, and be we learned in Gods feare, and take we heed henceforward how wee ſtorme againſt Gods Voices as wee doe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>39</label> leſt as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> tels vs, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. we be found fighters againſt God. And take we heede withall how we cenſure Gods Voices, as we doe, bringing with vs cutious eares, which heare more to deſcant on the Miniſter, then to profit by his miniſterie. For in that we cenſure the Miniſter of God, we ſeeme to cenſure God himſelfe, ſuch the Miniſter, he is but the Lords Voice, the Word it is Gods owne Word, and the Miniſter, he is but the voice to publiſh it. And therefore as <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke the indignities done to his Embaſſadours by the Princes of the children of <hi>Ammon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 10.</note> as done vnto himſelfe, and ſo reuenged them: ſo though euen Princes, neuer ſo great ones of the world, wrong and abuſe the Embaſſadours of the Lord, theſe Voices of the Lord; God he will take the abuſe as done vnto himſelfe, and will one day repay it home.</p>
            <p>Henceforth then let the people take heed how they heare, ſith it is Gods Word they heare, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered onely by mans voice. And let the Miniſter alſo take heed how hee ſpeake, ſince it is Gods Word, and not his owne, which hee is to ſpeake, that ſo, there being this ſweet harmony betweene the Hearer of Gods Word, and the Speaker,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20580:13"/>there may be more true deuotion in the heart, and leſſe cenſuring prattle with the tongue. And ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Miniſters dutie, proceed we onward to the Peoples. It is ſo, you ſee, that the Miniſter, he is the Lords Voice; and therefore as it is all our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to reuerence the Lord, ſo is it alſo our duties to beare reſpect vnto his Voices. For the Church, it is Chriſts Spouſe, and the Congregation of the faithfull: the Church of God cannot better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe her loue to Chriſt her Husband, who is in Heauen, then by a due reſpect vnto his Voices, who are heere on earth. Now the due reſpect of a louing Wife vnto her Husband, conſiſts in three maine duties. Firſt, to loue him: Secondly, to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh him: Thirdly, to obey him. All which, the Church of God, and Congregation of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe ſhe is the Spouſe of Chriſt, is bound to impart vnto his Voices, for they are Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers heere ouearth, to receiue for him theſe pledges of our loue: And <hi>ſo alſo</hi> (ſaith our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) <hi>he that receiueth you, receiueth me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10.40.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now we are firſt to loue Chriſts Voices: and this is the thing the Apoſtle beſeecheth at our hands, to haue them all in ſingular loue,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.12, 13.</note> who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour amongſt vs, who are ouer vs in the Lord, who admoniſh vs: to loue ſuch, with a more then ordinarie, with a ſingular loue for their workes ſake; and we are bound to loue them in two reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects: Firſt, becauſe they are Chriſts, his Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, ſent vnto vs with an Ambaſſie of Peace, beſeeching vs in Chriſts ſtead,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note> to bee reconciled
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20580:14"/>vnto God. Now if we loue the Prince of Peace; needs muſt we loue theſe Embaſſadors of Peace: and if we loue <hi>CHRIST IESVS,</hi> who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Word, needs muſt we loue them, who are the Voices, to publiſh, and proclaime this Word. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, we are bound to loue them, becauſe they loue vs, they watch ouer our ſoules; nay, they loue many a man, better then hee loues himſelfe: for theſe Voices,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hier.</hi> 9.1.</note> they oftentimes with <hi>Ieremy,</hi> carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with them, whole fountains of teares, in their head, and in their heart, &amp; draw from theſe Wels, with the two Buckets of their eyes, ſuch abundance of teares, that their eyes ſhead teares day and night, for their ſinnes, who ſeldome, or neuer ſhead a teare for their owne ſinnes: And therefore good reaſon haue we, to loue theſe Voices, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe not to hate them, as too too many doe, who little better eſteeme of them,<note place="margin">Gen. 16.12.</note> then of <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael:</hi> their hand againſt euery man, and euery mans band againſt them.</p>
            <p>I will ſay thus much, to the honour, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of this famous Citie; There is no Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnder heauen more reſpects theſe Voices, if they be the Lords Voices indeed, then the more graue, and diſcreeter Citizens: And as for the reſt, they loue them too, but not with ſo good diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for they loue them in a manner, as the Ape doth her yong ones: they loue them ſo importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, that they kill them. And therefore it were to be wiſht, they would loue them a little more, in louing them a little leſſe, while they giue the Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20580:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>a breathing time, to follow the Apoſtles rule to his beloued <hi>Timothy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim 4.13.</note> To giue attendance to reading, and to exhortation, and to doctrine; that there may be a breathing while, for the Voices, to giue attendance to reading: as well as all to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, and to doctrine: For the Voices, they will be ſo much the better able, to teach others by their doctrine, when they haue firſt taught them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by their reading.</p>
            <p>Now as wee are bound, to loue the Lords Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; ſo can we not better expreſſe our loue vnto them, then in cheriſhing them. For farre bee it, that the Lords Voices ſhould be fedde, like meere voyces indeed; onely with ayre: and that their maintenance ſhould bee the peoples courteſie and beneuolence; for this, it were a diſhonour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and a great abaſing to the Miniſterie. The very Heathens tell vs as much.<note place="margin">Ptut. Mor.</note> For <hi>Plutarch</hi> tels vs of a <hi>Laconian,</hi> who ſeeing a Collector going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and gathering the peoples deuotions for the gods: O (ſaith he) I will now make no more rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of the gods; ſo long as I ſee them goe a begging, and to bee poorer then my ſelfe. And would not, thinke you, many a churliſh <hi>Nabal,</hi> and repining <hi>Laban</hi> of theſe dayes, bee ready to fall into the ſame diſdaine of God, and of his Voices, if the Offals onely of their reuenues, and cruell mercies of their purſe, were the ſtay, and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Miniſters life. This it were great pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, it ſhould be ſo; and hope ſuggeſts the beſt, that it wil neuer be. For were it ſo; as in the ſame <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20580:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>we reade,<note place="margin">Plut. Mor.</note> of one <hi>Philippus,</hi> a Prieſt amongſt the Heathen, ſo poore, that hee beg'd for his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and yet hee would goe about, and tell how happy he ſhould be. When (quoth one) will this be? When I am dead (ſaith he.) Why, (then poore fellow (quoth the other) thou art too blame, thou dieſt not quickly, that thou mayſt be happy. Euen thus ſhould the Lords poore Voices bee flouted of the world. The Lord is our portion, ſay the Voices, and wee ſhall bee happy; but when, ſaith the world, ſhall you haue this portion, that ye may be happy? When we dye, ſay the Voices. Why, then ſayes the world; yee are too blame, ye dye not quickly, to be happy in Heauen, whom the world hath tooke an order with, neuer to bee happy on earth. But this, it is the voice of the ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> who haue euill will at Sion, and had rather put a Church into their purſe, then empty their purſe vpon the Church.</p>
            <p>For you (beloued) the Lords Voices are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded better things of you, how regardfull of them you haue alwayes beene, and how carefull you be,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 4.</note> not onely with the good Shunamite, to prouide them a Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, a Table, &amp; a Stoole, when they turne in vnto you: but to ſend them away, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did his Brethren;<note place="margin">Gen. 42.</note> with their Sacks full of Corne, and euery man his money in his Sacks mouth: meat for the belly, and money for the back. For which care of yours, in cheriſhing the Lords Voices; the bleſſing of Heauen, and the farneſſe of the earth, be your great reward. And
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20580:15"/>may they euer liue, regiſtred in the Kalendar of Saints, who already haue, or hereafter ſhall, more like the Primitiues of old; then the hold-faſt Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſiues of theſe times, thus bring in part of their Poſſeſſions, and lay it downe at the Apoſtles feet, bringing an offering, to the worke of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle; to this ſo worthy a Worke. Now as wee are to loue, and cheriſh; ſo are wee alſo to obey the Lords Voices. And this is it the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts you vnto, Heb. 13. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>17</label> 
               <hi>Obey them which haue the ouer ſight of you, and ſubmit your ſelues: for they watch for your ſoules, as they that muſt giue account, for them vnto God, that they may doe it with ioy, and not with griefe: for that is vnprofitable for you.</hi> You are then to obey Gods Miniſter: becauſe God hath ſet him, as a watchma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer your ſoules, &amp; he muſt giue an account to God for your ſoules. Now if ye doe what hee commands you from God, his ſhall be the ioy; and yours the crowne. But if yet will be ſtiffenecked, and not obey; though his bee the griefe, to ſee his Miniſterie take no better ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect amongſt you, yours ſhall be the perill. For if hee giue vp his account of your ſoules, with griefe of heart, for your diſobedience to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt: this, it is vnprofitable, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for you, and not for him. And therefore, as you tender your ſoules, obey the Lords Voices, which watch ouer your ſoules. Giue an obedient eare to the Lords Voices, to heare them: and an obedient heart to the Lord himſelfe, to feare him, that yee may be bleſſed. For in the 30. of <hi>Deuteronomie,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>20</label>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20580:16"/>there be three wayes ſet downe; the three rodes, by which we come to bleſſednes: the firſt is, by lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Lord thy God: the ſecond, by obeying his Voice: and the third, by cleauing vnto him; ſo that, if thou loue the Lord, becauſe he is thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; if thou cleaue vnto him, becauſe he is thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niour; if thou obey his Voice, becauſe hee is thy Lord: thou, and thy Seed, ſhall liue, and bee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon earth. For if thou obey diligently the Voice of the Lord, the Lord in the 28. of <hi>Deut.</hi> pronourices thee <hi>Bleſſed in the Citie,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>and bleſſed in the field,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>bleſsed in the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of the ground,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>bleſſed in thy comming in, and in thy going out,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> 
               <hi>bleſſed in thy ſtorehouſes, bleſsed in all thou ſet'ſt thine hand vnto.</hi> Thus ſhall the man bee bleſſed, that obeyes the Voice of the Lord. And therefore all ye, who deſire bleſſednes, heare, and obey, that yee may eate the good things of the Land. And thus now, you ſee, how, for the Lords ſake, whoſe Spouſe the Church is, you are to loue, to cheriſh, and to obey, the Lords Voices: Now let euery faithfull Chriſtian, which is a member of the true Church, the Spouſe of Chriſt, plight faith to Chriſt, the Husband of this Spouſe, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this Chriſtian dutie: which God ſo requires at our hands. And ſo from the Voice, come we to ſee the nature of the Voice. It is a cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Voice: The Lords Voice Cryoth: and neede had the Voice be a Crying Voice: for it hath a Citie to Cry in, and a whiſpering ſtill Voice is not for the Citie: for this, none could heare. Nay, an
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20580:16"/>ordinarie ſpeaking voice, is not for the Citie: for this few could heare. And therefore, the Voice, being ſent vnto the Citie, it is a Crying Voice, that all might heare it. And thus doth God, by ſending a Crying Voice vnto them, take away all colourable pretences, and excuſes from the City. For, had a ſtill voice, or an ordinarie ſpeaking voice, come vnto them, their plea had been; <hi>non audiuimus:</hi> the Voice, it was ſo ſtill, that, what, for the clamours of the Citie, wee heard it not. And therefore, the Voice, it is a Crying Voice: that all might heare it: and none might haue excuſe, wherewith to cloke his finne. Now then the Voice, it is a Crying Voice: in three reſpects. Firſt, it is a crying Voice, to make an out-cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt crying ſins. Secondly, it is a crying Voice, to rouze and awake the Citie, dead aſleepe in ſinne: which no Voice, but a crying Voice could rouze. Thirdly, it is a crying Voice, to leaue the Citie without excuſe: to take away all excuſe from the Citie. For the firſt, the Voice, it is a crying Voice, to make an out cry againſt crying ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Sinne, it hath got a voice in the world: yea, and that a lowd crying Voice, in the eares of GOD. <hi>Cains</hi> ſinne of murther, it had a crying Voice: for <hi>Abels</hi> bloud, in the fourth of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> cryes in Gods eares for vengeance. The ſinne of <hi>Sodome,</hi> it had a crying Voice: For in the 18. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> the cry of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> is ſaid to be great in the eares of the Lord. And in theſe laſt, and worſe dayes of the world, ſinne hath more lift vp her
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20580:17"/>voice then euer: for ſinne hath got a roring voice: &amp; now ſin, which before did but cry to heauen for vengeance; it now roares for vengeance: Now that there be many roarers abroad in the world, who, becauſe their father the Diuell, is ſtiled by Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> in the laſt Chapter of his firſt Epiſtle, a roaring Lyon; bluſh not to ſtile themſelues, his roaring Whelpes, his roaring Boyes. And theſe roaring Boyes, ſend roaring out of their Pot-guns, in their drunken fits, nothing elſe, but fearefull blaſphemies againſt the God of Heauen. Now then, ſince ſinne hath not onely got a crying, but euen a roaring voice in the world; high time it is, God ſhould haue at leaſtwiſe a crying Voice in the world, to make an out-cry againſt theſe crying, and theſe roaring ſinnes: and that for two reſpects. The one, in reſpect of God; the other, in reſpect of man. Firſt in reſpect of God; it is moſt neceſſarie, God ſhould haue a crying Voice abroad in the world. For ſhould ſinne ſtill goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in the world, thus vncontrouled, with a cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a roaring voice, it would carry the whole world to hell with moſt voices: For the voice of blaſphemie would quite drowne the voice of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the voice of Prayer, it would bee turned into the voice of curſing; and where no voice were heard, but the crying voice of ſinne, all men would learne to ſpeake no language, but the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Diuell: all men would bee of one tongue: but that tongue dipt in boyling Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, to ſpeake nothing but Blaſphemie; the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20580:17"/>of the damned; that tongue dipt in gall, to ſpeake of nothing but curſedneſſe and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; that tongue dipt in bloud, to ſpeake of nothing but bloud and ſlaughter; ſo aduancing it ſelfe, euen to the Throne of God: if it were poſſible, to pull God out of his Throne: one while crying out, <hi>Vbi eſt Deus?</hi> Where is God? another while crying out, <hi>Non reſpicit Deus;</hi> God regardeth not: yet another while flatly roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out, <hi>Non eſt Deus,</hi> There is no GOD. This, and farre more worſe then this, would bee the language of the world, were there no voyce heard in the world, but the crying voyce of ſinne: God therefore, to ſtop the mouth of the Diuell, who thus goes about to deface his glory: ſcoming at his power, with <hi>Vbi eſt Deus?</hi> Where is God? deriding his prouidence, with, <hi>Non reſpicit Deus:</hi> God regardeth not: Nay more then this; ſeeking to pull God out of his Throne, with, <hi>Non eſt Deus:</hi> There is no God: God, hee alſo ſends a crying Voyce into the world, to make an outcry againſt this Cry of ſinne, and to drowne and confound this curſed language of the world, inuented in hell, &amp; learned of the Deuil: which being of a far high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er reach, then euer <hi>Babel</hi> could poſſibly haue been, would towre vp higher then to Heauen; euen to the Throne of God, if it were poſſible, to dethrone that great Monarch of the world, with <hi>Non est Deus,</hi> There is no God. And now, that Gods crying voyce is heard in the world, the better part of the world hath learned the holy tongue, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20580:18"/>words of piety, are now more often heard, then words of blaſphemy; and the Voyce of prayer, is now more frequent, then the Voyce of curſing: So that now, no longer, Where is God? for, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houa in coelis:</hi> Our God, he is in heauen; no longer now God regardeth not: for our God, as he is in heauen, ſo beholds hee all things that are done, both in heauen and earth, and his prouidence go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes all things.<note place="margin">Wiſd. 14.</note> No longer now, <hi>Non eſt Deus,</hi> There is no God; for our God, he is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Reu. 1.4.</note> He, who is, who was, and is to come: our God, hee is from all eternity.</p>
            <p>Now, as God thus ſends a crying Voyce into the world, to vindicate his glory from the vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of men,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.18.</note> who elſe would <hi>withhold the truth of God in vnrighteouſneſſe:</hi> So doth hee alſo, in great compaſſion vnto man, ſend his crying Voyce into the world, to outcry crying ſinnes, leſt crying ſinnes, ſtill crying in Gods eares for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſhould pull downe the vials of Gods wrath, to conſume man from off the face of the earth: for the crying voyce of ſinne, is ſtill importuning the hand of Iuſtice, with one plague or other, to cut off the ſinner. And one while it cals for a ſecond De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge, to drowne the world, for the ouerflowings of vngodlineſſe, which are in the world: yet another while, it calls for a famine, to puniſh the want and ſcarſity of good men: yet another while, it calls for peſtilence and the ſword, to puniſh our abuſe of health and happineſſe. And thus is the voyce of ſinne ſtill vrging the hand of Iuſtice, to write
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20580:18"/>bitter things againſt the ſinner: but the crying Voyce of mercy, which God, for the good of man, ſends into the world, ſpeakes better things both from God to man, and for man to God. And it firſt ſpeakes from God to man, that man would preuent puniſhment by penitence, that man would preuent a ſecond floud, to drowne the world for ſinne, by firſt drowning his ſinne in a floud of leares: leauing his crying ſinnes, and falling a cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his ſins. Now as this crying Voyce ſpeaks mercy from God to man, ſo doth it alſo ſpeake for mercy, vnto God for man: for in the ſecond of <hi>Ioel,</hi> the Prieſts, theſe crying Voyces of the Lord, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>17</label> they weepe betweene the porch and the Altar, and cry to God; <hi>Spare thy people, O Lord, and giue not thine heritage ouer to reproch;</hi> and God in the 18. and 19. verſes, to ſhew how much hee accepts the cry of his Voyces, the cryes and prayers of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, which they powre before him for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, himſelfe vouchſafes a gracious reply, and makes the anſwer, how that at the cry of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, he cannot but be iealous ouer his Land, and ſpare his people, and giue them their hearts deſire, corne, wine and oyle, and freedome from their enemies: ſuch is the force of prayer for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in the Lords Miniſters mouth, if it be feruent from the heart. Now then, ye people of the Lord, if ye haue any care, or regard at all of your ſoules, learne to diſtinguiſh betweene the cry of voyces, that knowing which cry againſt your ſoules good, and which cry for the good of your ſoules, you
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20580:19"/>may be able to diſcerne, which you are to heare, and obey, which to ſhut your eares againſt, and to auoyd. You ſee heere there bee three crying voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces abroad in the world; The firſt is the crying, nay the roaring voyce of the Deuill, and this voyce cries vnto you to breathe defiance againſt Heauen, and to write your names in the earth, with the red inke of bloud, or the blacke inke of helliſh villany: This voyce cries vnto you with wicked <hi>Kain,</hi> to murther a righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> it cries vnto you to play the traitor with <hi>Iudas,</hi> it cries vnto you to take away another mans poſſeſſion with <hi>Ahab,</hi> it cries vnto you to ſteale a wedge of gold with <hi>Achan,</hi> it cries vnto you to play the drunken Sot with <hi>Nabal,</hi> it cries vnto you to play the vncharitable Miſer with <hi>Diues,</hi> it cries vnto you to dye your ſoules of the Deuils hue, in the blacke deeds of darkneſſe and of wickedneſſe. Now the ſecond crying voyce which is abroad in the world, is the crying voyce of ſinne, and this cries to heauen for a puniſhment for ſinners, it cries vnto the clowds to deny the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner raine, it cries vnto the ſunne to deny the ſinner light, it cries vnto the earth to deny the ſinner food, it cries to Mercy not to regard the ſinner, it cries to Iuſtice to renounce the ſinner, it cries to hell to receiue the ſinner, and it cries for tortures to torment the ſinner: this is the crying voyce of ſinne, which is neuer with vs, but is ſtill againſt vs. Now the third and laſt crying voyce, which is Gods crying Voyce of Mercy, this cries vnto you, not to play <hi>Kains</hi> part, and to kill, but to loue
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20580:19"/>thy brother as thy ſelfe; not to play <hi>Iudas</hi> part, and betray, but to obey from the heart thoſe which are ſet ouer you; not to play <hi>Ahabs</hi> part, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, but to giue to euery man his owne; not to play <hi>Achans</hi> part, and to ſteale, but to worke euery man with his own hands, &amp; to eat his bread in the ſweat of his browes; not to play <hi>Nabals</hi> part, and be drunke, but to be ſober, to watch and to play; not to play <hi>Diues</hi> part, and to be miſerable, but to doe good, to diſtribute, to bee to all men charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and then againe, it cries vnto you, as you would haue the clowds drop raine, ſo let your eyes drop teares for your ſinnes; as you would haue the earth be fruitful, ſo to be fruitfull in good works as you would haue the ſunne giue light, ſo to walke as children of light; as you would haue heauen, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape hell, ſo to haue your conuerſation in heauen, while ye liue on earth. This is the Voyce of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which is euer with vs, and neuer is againſt vs.</p>
            <p>Now chuſe you which of theſe three voyces will you heare: the Deuils voyce, you ſee, how it comes vnto you with a word cloathed with death, and playes the Orator for hell, to gaine right to your ſoule through vnrighteous practices; and will you heare this voyce, to obey and follow it? Why, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it you may; but know where it leades: it leads to the paths of death, &amp; high-way to damnation. The crying voyce of ſinne, this you heare, how it cries to, heauen againſt you, and ſtill in the end proues a backward friend to thoſe her vaſſals, who obey ſinne in the luſt thereof; though at firſt, the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20580:20"/>better to ſerue her turn, ſhe fawne vpon them: and will you now bee wonne by the entiſing voyce of ſinne, to follow and obey it in the luſt thereof? why, follow it you may, but it threatens your deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; for ſinne will one day pay her ſeruants their wages home, and will requite their euill life which was ſpent in her ſeruice, with euerlaſting death, which is their wages for their ſeruice:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> for, <hi>the wages of ſinne is death;</hi> and therefore as you tender your ſoules, redeemed by Chriſts precious bloud from the power of ſinne and Satan, captiuate not your ſoules againe, by liſtning to the entiſements of ſin, and prouocations of the Deuill; but lend your eares onely to the Lords crying Voyce of mercy, attend only this bleſſed Voyce which cryes abroad in the world, to bring ſinners home againe to God by repentance: and if you ſhut your eares, the dores of your ſoule, againſt all other entiſing voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſinne and Satan, and open them onely to the Lords crying Voyce, to prepare a way for the King of glory to enter in: aſſure your ſelues, ſuch ſhall be the peace and ioy of your ſoules, that you ſhall haue heauen in your ſoules in this life, and your ſoules ſhall haue heauen in another life. And ſo much for the firſt reaſon, why the Voyce, it is a crying Voyce.</p>
            <p>Now ſecondly, the Voyce, it is a crying Voyce, to rouze and awake the dead &amp; ſecure City: dead aſleepe in ſin, which no voyce but a crying Voyce could rouze: and this collection fitly ariſes from ſome variety of interpretation of the word in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20580:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Originall, which is here rendred a City; for (as <hi>Cal uin</hi> hath obſerued it) ſome read it, <hi>Vox Iebouae ad ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit atem;</hi> ſome againe, <hi>Ad exper gefaciendum clamat.</hi> Some read it, The Voyce of the Lord crieth to the City. Some againe read it; The Voyce of the Lord crieth to rouze, &amp; to awake: which implies the great deadneſs &amp; ſecurity of the Citie, which could not be awaked without a crying Voyce; for as our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauior, being to raiſe dead <hi>Lazarus</hi> from death to life, is ſaid to cry with a loud voyce, <hi>Clamauit vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce magna</hi> (ſaith the text) he cryed with a loud voyce,<note place="margin">Iohn 11.</note> 
               <hi>Lazarus, come forth;</hi> ſo our bleſſed Sauior being to raiſe the dead ſinner, dead in ſins &amp; treſpaſſes, as it is <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. he makes his Voyces crying Voyces, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">verſ. </seg>1</label> to cry vnto the ſinner to come forth of the graue of ſin: <hi>Surge qui dormis, Awake thou that ſleepeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>and ſtand vp from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as the City Hieruſalem had need of this crying Voyce: euen ſo hath our Hieruſalem, this City of ours. Our Citizens complaine, It is now a dead world, a dead time, and there is little ſtirring in the world, little trading; but they may more iuſtly complaine in another ſenſe, that it is a dead world indeed, men carrying about with them li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bodies, but dead ſoules; and, There is little ſtirring in the world; for iniquity hath got the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand, and iets aboue honeſty euery where; ſo that honeſty ſtirres little abroad, for ſhe hath little trading in the world: while wicked men, who make a trade of ſinning by their euill cuſtomes, make the greater part of the world their cuſtomers: and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20580:21"/>therefore if euer the Lords crying Voyces cryed to dead mens eares, to heare the word of the Lord, now is the time; for the greater part of men, like the widow which liueth in pleaſure,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.6.</note> are dead while they liue. And could you but euery weeke haue bils brought you in, to ſignifie within the City li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and without, how many ſoules dye in a weeke; ſome of a ſurfet of drunkenneſſe, ſome of a ſwelling tympany of pride, ſome of the burning feauer of malice, ſome of the dropſie of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſome of one or other diſeaſe of the ſoule; you would bleſſe your ſelues, to ſee moſt mens bodies to be but liuing Sepulchers for dead ſoules: and you would pity the great taske which is impoſed vpon the Lords crying Voyces, to heare them cry to dead mens eares, which hearing will not heare, and to dead mens harts, which will not vnderſtand: and therefore blame we not the Lords Voyces, for their importunate crying in our eares, crying vnto vs in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, crying at all ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; for they cry moſt vnto dead men.</p>
            <p>And well ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quam difficile ſargit, quem mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les male conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinis premit: ſed tamen ſurgit poſt vocem mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, Auguſt. in Joan. tract. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> Hard it is to awake a ſinner, whom cuſtome hardens in his ſinne, and yet ſuch a ſinner, hee may bee wakened, if you often call vpon him for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. At much and often crying then, euen the dead ſhall heare the Voyce of the Sonne of God, and they that heare it; ſhall liue: Cry then ſtill, yee Voyces of the Lord, whom God hath made the Cities Criers, to cry loſt children home againe to him their heauenly Father, by repentance: and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20580:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpare not to cry, whileſt voyce and breath doe ſerue to cry: and though ye cry to dead mens eares, yet is not your labour in vaine in the Lord: for Truth it ſelfe hath ſaid it in the fift of <hi>Iohn,</hi> for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of your labours: <hi>Verily, verily I ſay vnto you,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>25</label> 
               <hi>the dead ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of God, and they that heare it, ſhal liue.</hi> And this is alſo comfort for the ſinner, that though he be dead in ſinnes, nay with <hi>Lazarus,</hi> dead foure daies: Dead the firſt day by delight in ſin, dead the ſecond day by conſent to ſinne, dead the third day, by the act of ſinne, dead the fourth day, by a cuſtomary ſinning: ſo that it may bee ſaid of him, as of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he now ſtinkes in the noſtrils of the Lord: yet if this dead ſinner will but heare the Voyces of the Lord, crying and crying againe, in precept vpon precept, exhortation vpon exhortation, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> come forth thou ſinner: how come forth? why, S. <hi>Anguſtine</hi> tels thee how; <hi>quando conſiteris, procedis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt in John. ibid.</note> when thou doſt confeſſe thy ſinne to God, thou commeſt forth of the graue of ſinne. And if the ſinner thus come forth, vomiting vp, as it were, his ſinnes, which are a burthen to his conſcience, the ſtomach of his ſoule, by an humble confeſſion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; Truth it ſelfe hath ſaid it, this dead ſinner, he ſhall liue. And though hee come forth of the graue of ſinne, bound like <hi>Lazarus,</hi> hand and foot, bound with the chaines of his ſinnes: yet Chriſt ſhall giue his Miniſters charge ouer him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, looſe him from his ſinnes, abſolue him and let him goe in peace. And therefore to draw
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20580:22"/>vp all vnto an end: Let not Gods Voyces deſpaire of doing good, though they cry moſt vnto dead men, becauſe Truth hath ſaid it for the comfort of their labour, <hi>The dead ſhall heare the Voyce of the Sonne of GOD:</hi> and let not dead men, men dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes, if they heare the voyce of the Sonne of God, deſpaire of mercy; for Truth hath alſo ſaid it, to their comfort, <hi>They that heare the Voyce of the Sonne of God, ſhall liue:</hi> they that heare Chriſts <hi>Surgite mortui,</hi> Ariſe ye dead in this life, and liue the life of Grace in this world: ſhall heare Chriſts <hi>Surgite mortui:</hi> Ariſe ye dead after this life, and liue the life of glory in the world to come. And ſo come we to the third and laſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why the Voyce, it is a crying Voyce, and that is to take away al excuſe from the City, of <hi>Nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> audiuimus,</hi> We neuer heard the voyce. For man, ſuch is his folly, when once ſin layes open his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, he flatters himſelfe, all is well, if hee haue but a cloake to caſt vpon his ſinne; for ſo our firſt Parents, no ſooner had they ſinned, but they ſeeke for a cloake to palliate their ſinne;<note place="margin">Gen 3.</note> and <hi>Eue,</hi> ſhee muſt be the cloake for <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent the cloake for <hi>Eues</hi> ſinne. And all we, <hi>Adams</hi> ſinfull poſterity, haue worne this cloake of excuſe euen almoſt thred-bare by long vſage of it, in pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liating of our ſinnes: And we cloake Drunkenneſs with good fellowſhip; wee cloake Couetouſneſſe with good thriftineſſe; wee cloake Pride with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and comelineſſe: there is no ſinne but wee haue a cloake for it, or elſe, if wee want a cloake
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20580:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>for our ſinne, we are ready to fetch a cloake from heauen, and euen to accuſe God himſelfe, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe our ſinne: As S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> tels vs of a priſoner at the Barre, who being conuict of felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, pleads his pardon vpon this, how that God had ſo ordained him to be a Thiefe, and therefore he could no other doe but ſteale: For who euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the will of God? But the Iudge anſwered him very well; If God hath ordained thee to bee a Thiefe and to ſteale, God hath alſo ordained mee to bee a Iudge, and to hang thee for thy theeuerie.</p>
            <p>Now as we ſpare not, thus to accuſe God, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe our ſinne: So are we moſt ready to excuſe our ſelues, by accuſing of Gods Word: and the whole world is ſet on this: And ſome Nations in the world, thinke it excuſe ſufficient for their ſin, that they neuer had theſe crying Voices of the Lord, to ſound his Word and precepts in their eares: but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tels them: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art inexcuſable O man,</hi> who makeſt this thy Plea. For thou haſt a viſible word, which, though it preach not to thine eares, yet doth it preach vnto thine eyes: and makes thy two eyes, the two witneſſes of Gods glory and mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee. For the Sunne, which giues thee light, the ayre thou breatheſt in, the earth thou feedeſt on: theſe be dumbe Preachers,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.19.</note> and preach Gods mercy to thine eyes: and no Nation is there in the world, but it hath this kinde of preaching in it.<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.3.</note> For <hi>there is no ſpeech nor language</hi> (ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20580:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>where the voice of theſe Preachers is not heard. And therefore this is enough to euince the worlds vnthankefulnes vnto God, for the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his mercies, &amp; to leaue the world (as the Apoſtle witneſſeth) without excuſe.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> But yet God, he farther takes excuſe from man (ſo loth hee is man ſhould caſt away his ſoule with excuſes) and he writes the Notions of his Law, euen in the heart of euery man:<note place="margin">Rom. 2.14. &amp; 15.</note> making euery mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to be his Accuſer, or excuſer before God: Nay, more then this: yet farther, to take excuſe from Man; God, hee not onely giues a viſible word to preach vnto our eyes, nor onely the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Law, written in our hearts, but he ſends an audible Word amongſt vs, his Voices to cry and proclaime his Law in our eares, and to reuiue it in our hearts; ſo, that wee can plead no excuſe at all for our ſelues: Our eyes are our witneſſes, which dayly behold Gods mercies: our hearts are our witneſſes,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.</note> which ſhew the effect of the Law written in the heart: and our eares are our wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, which dayly heare Gods crying Voices (and they cannot chuſe but heare them, becauſe they be crying Voices) ſtill crying vnto vs, This is the way, walke in it. O let not vs then, ſith God is ſo carefull to take excuſe from vs, make excuſes to our ſelues, to deſtroy our ſoules. Let vs not ſhut our eyes from beholding Gods mercie; let vs not ſhut our eares from liſtning to his iudgements; and let vs not harden our hearts againſt his feare, to diſobey his Law, and diſhonour his Name: but
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20580:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſith hee is ſo carefull to preach his Name to our eyes, to our hearts, and to our eares: let vs obey theſe diuers cals of mercy, that we may be ſaued: otherwiſe if we doe, no excuſe you ſee will ſerue, but we muſt vtterly periſh.</p>
            <p>Now if any Nation in the world be left inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable in theſe reſpects: this little Goſhen of ours, this little Iland of ours, is moſt without excuſe, which (as ſpeakes the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi>) in his 11. Chapter, is ful of the Knowledge of the Lord, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>9</label> euen as the waters couer the Sea: So that England is not ſo much enuironed with the waters of the Sea, as it is full of the Knowledge of the Lord, and of his Word: euery nooke and angle of our Land, hauing a plentifull increaſe of the Lords Voices in it, to cry &amp; proclaime the Lords meſſage in our eares. This famous Citie (more eſpecially) it is ſo full of the Lords crying Voices, that ſome ſticke not to complaine, They haue too much knowledge now adayes: but take they heed how they complaine, they haue too much, leſt God for our vnthankefulnes puniſh vs, as he doth many other Nations, with little enough. And let vs know thus much, to make vs carefull, to make good vſe of our knowledge: the more knowledge we haue, the leſſe excuſe wee haue for our ſinne: And the more the Lords Voices cry amongſt vs, the more ſhall be our puniſhments, if wee obey them not:<note place="margin">Luke 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> For the Seruant that knowes his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters will, and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtripes. And therefore, as you deſire to ſecure
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20580:24"/>the Citie from the Lords Rodde, and your owne ſoules from his conſuming wrath: Sith God, to leaue you without excuſe, ſends crying Voices vnto you, in mercy to forewarne you: lend your eares, and hearts, to heare and obey that, which the Lords Voice cryeth to your Citie: For the Lords Voice cryeth to the Citie.</p>
            <p>It is a great and publique taske for the Lords Voices to Cry vnto a Citie: And therefore, <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> beeing ſent to <hi>Nineueh</hi> that great Citie, faine would he flie from the preſence of the Lord, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be the Lords Cryer in ſo great a Citie; till the Word of the Lord comes vnto him the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time,<note place="margin">Ion. 3.1. &amp; 2.</note> commanding him, Ariſe, and goe to <hi>Niniueh</hi> that great Citie, and preach vnto it the preaching that I bid thee. Now as it fared with <hi>Ionah,</hi> ſo it fares with moſt of the Lords Voices, but that the Lord is with them, and they preach the preaching which hee commands them, they would draw back, as fearing to cry vnto a Citie. And therefore when the Lords Voices, out of this and ſuch like publike places, cry vnto your Citie, blame not the Voices, for the Voices, they of themſelues are ſlow enough to Cry vnto a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but that the Lord in mercy to a Citie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels them, as hee did <hi>Ionah,</hi> to ariſe and goe vnto the Citie, and preach the preaching hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them, which ye are the more willingly to heare; becauſe they preach no other, but the preaching which God bids them preach. And therefore blame me not, though (who am I the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20580:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>meaneſt of Gods Voices) if I ſhew vnto you how the Lords quarrell with this Citie in my Text, agrees in ſome ſort to this famous Citie. For let vs but paralell Gods benefits beſtowed on both theſe Cities, and then ſee whether both Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties haue beene ſo thankefull vnto God for theſe his benefits, as they ought to be. Firſt, for Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, this Citie in my Text, ſaith God to her, in the fourth and fift <hi>verſe</hi> of this preſent Chapter, <hi>Remember my louing kindneſses of old, how I brought thee out of the Land of Egypt, and deliuered thee out of the houſe of Seruants:</hi> nor onely ſo, but gaue thee <hi>Moſes, Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> for thy guides. And hath not God done this, and much more for our Citie? Let vs remember his louing kindneſſes of old, how God, he hath deliuered vs from <hi>Egypt,</hi> Romes tyrannie, which in the 11. of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> is ſtiled to vs by the name of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> and hath freed vs from the houſe of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, from the ſlauiſh and Egyptian bondage of an vſurning <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the Pope; who would ſtill haue made both Prince and People, Seruants and Vaſſals to his painted holineſſe: and who in one thing was more then a <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> in that he ſought to deſtroy by cruell death, not onely all the Males, but Females too of the Stock of <hi>Sem;</hi> who profeſt themſelues members of the true Church: nor onely this hath God done for vs; but hee hath alſo giuen vs a <hi>Moſes;</hi> a moſt gracious King: As he alſo gaue vs a <hi>Miriam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queene</hi> Elzabeth.</note> a gracious Queene of happy memory, deare Siſter to our gracious <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:20580:25"/>both a nurſing Father and Mother to our Church; and an <hi>Aaron,</hi> a holy and a learned Clergie, to guide and gouerne vs, euer ſince we ſet foote out of this blinde Egypt, in the way of peace and truth. Nor onely this did God for the people of the Iewes; but in the fift Verſe, hee bids them remember, how <hi>Balak.</hi> King of Moab con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted their deſtruction; and how <hi>Balaams</hi> Curſe, God, he turned it into a bleſſing vnto them. And hath not God done this &amp; much more for our Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? For let vs but remember what in Eightie eight was conſulted againſt vs; when Pope <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> was ſent for to bleſſe the Nauie, and to curſe Gods people: How the Lord turned Pope <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> Curſe into a Bleſſing vnto vs: let vs remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber theſe old louing kindneſſes of the Lord, and ſo acknowledge the righteouſneſſe of the Lord, his faithfulneſſe and his mercy to vs: theſe be the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, which God, hee would not haue his Citie Ieruſalem, to forget paralell to the benefits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on vs: which farre bee it, this our Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, this famous Citie of ours ſhould once forget.</p>
            <p>And thus we ſee, God, he is as kinde to vs, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hee was to his Hieruſalem; but let vs ſee in the ſecond place; whether we be not as vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto God for theſe his benefits, as euer Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem was. Hieruſalem betrayed her vnthankfull heart to God two maner of wayes: openly, by her manie rebellions; and ſecretly, by her hypocriſie: for her open rebellions, they are ſet downe in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20580:25"/>three next verſes following my Text, where you ſhal find treaſures of wickednes in the houſe of the wicked; ſcant meaſure, wicked balances, and a bag of deceitful weights, violence &amp; oppreſſion in the rich men, a deceitfull tongue in the mouth of all. Now God wondring at this, to ſee for all the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which he ſhewed to them, for all the crying &amp; preaching of his Voyces, ſuch groſſe ſinnes and enormities ſhould raigne in ſuch a City, a City ſo beloued, a City where his Word was ſo often preached, his Voyces ſtill crying to the City, hee breakes forth in admiration of the thing, <hi>Adhuc an ſunt?</hi> What, for all my mercies to you? What, for all the crying of my Voices to you? <hi>Adhuc an ſunt?</hi> Is it poſſible? Are there yet the treaſures of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the houſe of the wicked? ſcant meaſure, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked balances, a deceitfull weight? And are yet the rich men full of violence, and euery mans tongue deceitfull in his mouth? why, if it be ſo, high time it is to puniſh; and ſith mercy will not winne you, iudgement ſhall compell you. Wherupon in the very next verſes, God, he proceeds to iudgement: <hi>Therefore I will make thee ſicke in ſmiting thee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now look we to it, whether this Cities rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be not the rebellion of our City, whether Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems tranſgreſſion be not the ſin of our Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem; for firſt, are there not with vs the treaſures of wickedneſſe in the houſe of the wicked? Why, ſearch the coffers of Extortioners and griping op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſours, there ſhall you finde the treaſures of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; ſearch the coffers of corrupt Patrons, there
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20580:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:20580:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:20580:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo ſhall you finde the treaſures of iniquity; ſearch moſt mens coffers, &amp; more or leſſe, you ſhall bee ſure to find the treaſures of iniquity: ſo that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny it, but with vs the treaſures of wickednes do yet lodge in the houſe of the wicked. Now in the ſecond place, to make a full purſe, do not ſome amongſt vs make a ſcant meaſure, &amp; is there not with vs a ſcant meaſure, which is abominable, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked balances and a bag of deceitfull weights? this muſt we needs confeſſe that it is ſo: but it is the care of this Honorable City, as much as may be, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe it, that it be not ſo, &amp; might the delinquents in this kind ſmart for it, who bring Gods curſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the City, while they ſtriue to get a pony by abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, by a ſcant meaſure, which in the tenth verſe God hath pronounc'd abominable. The meaner ſort of offendors in this kinde, they are often met with, &amp; Iuſtice ouertakes them, but as <hi>Demetrius</hi> told <hi>Alexander,</hi> when <hi>Alexander</hi> cald him in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for his pyracy, <hi>I indeed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>play the Pyrate in two ſmall Erigots, &amp; am cald in queſtion for it, but great</hi> Alexander, <hi>he roames about, &amp; with two great armies robs the whole world, and no man dares to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll him for it:</hi> So many a petty <hi>Demetrius,</hi> who playes the falſe Marchant to get a penny or two by falſe balances and weights, is often moſt deſerued<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed for it: But there is a great <hi>Alexander,</hi> a great man in the world, who dealing in whole ſale, gets the gaine of whole pounds by falſe balan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and weights, and, as a ſip vnder his full ſaile, cuts it away a maine; ſo theſe in their whole ſale
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20580:27"/>carry ſmoothly away the gain of whole hundreths, by falſe balances and weights, and no man regards it, but the God of heauen, who heere inueighs againſt it by his Prophet, and threatens a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the City for it. Now in the third place, Hieruſalems ſinne was violence and oppreſſion in her rich men, her rich men were full of violence; &amp; what, is our Hieruſalem free from this? if the cry of the poore and the oppreſſed will free the City, ſo much the happier is the City: but it may be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that as our Prophet complained of the rich inhabitants of Hieruſalem, in the ſeuenth Chapter of this his Propheſie, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>4</label> how that the beſt of them <hi>was a brier, and the moſt vpright, ſharper then a thorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedge:</hi> So it may be feared, there be with vs many ſuch briers and thorne-hedges, who if a poore ſheep chance to fall into their hands, wil, like briers and thornes, make him leaue ſome of his fleece be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, and well it is many times, if they leaue him a whole skinne to ſleepe in: but let theſe rich oppreſſours, if any ſuch harbour within the City of God, henceſorward, take notice of it, that they are neither good friends to the City, nor to their owne ſoules: for theſe their vnlawfull practices bring a curſe vpon the one and vpon the other.</p>
            <p>Now in the fourth and laſt place, Hieruſalems ſinne was a lying and deceitfull tongue, for their tongue was deceitfull in their mouth. In their mouth, may ſome man ſay; what needs this addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? for how can the tongue be deceitfull, but in the mouth? but this, it is moſt Emphaticall, their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20580:28"/>tongue is deceitfull in their mouth, that is, they no ſooner open their mouth, but their tongue is ready to ſpeake deceit: ſo that deceit, it not onely lurks in the cloſet of the heart for ſome aſſaies, but it lies lurking vnder the tongue, and is ready ſtill in the porch of the mouth, to vent it ſelfe vpon all aſſaies. And this is it which the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">Ierem. 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>They haue taught their tongues to ſpeak lies,</hi> they need <hi>not ſtudy long for a deceitful anſwer,</hi> as occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerues; for they haue ſo well inured their tongues to a lye, that they haue it ſtill ready at their tongues end. This lying and deceitfull tongue, it was Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems ſinne, and ſo common amongſt them, that as the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">Ierem. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>Euery one was to take heed of his neighbour, and not to put trust in any bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for euery brother vſed deceit, and euery friend dealt deceitfully.</hi> And what, is our Hieruſalem free from this? Plaine-dealing men, who haue to deale with nimble trades-men, will tell you no; for alas, how many trades-mens tongues with vs now-a-daies are deceitfull in their mouth, who are as skilfull in the trade of lying, as of ſelling, hauing words at will to bring a poore ſimplician to their price? And as they thus can teach their tongues to ſpeake a lye, racking both credit and their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, for the aduantage of their wares, vſing faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning termes which ſound like muſick in the buyers eares, and like a Syrens ſong deceiue the ſimpler ſort: ſo doe they alſo teach their nimble hands to dance the meaſures, encroching on aduantage in their meaſure, to the defrauding of the buyers
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20580:28"/>purſe, if his eye be not ſtill their ouerſeer: ſo that now, if euer, the aduice holds good, <hi>Caueat emptor,</hi> let the buyer be wary, and take heed, for the world is full of nothing but deceit: and to ſay truth, moſt mens tongues are now-a-daies deceitfull in their mouth; for it is a nimble and a complementing world: and the world, like <hi>Naphthali,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.21.</note> giues goodly words; but it is not like <hi>Dorcas,</hi> full of good works:<note place="margin">Acts 9.36.</note> for, to ſpeake in the Prophet <hi>Dauids</hi> phraſe, you ſhall haue words as ſoft as butter,<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.21.</note> but this butter will not ſticke vpon your bread; for you ſhall haue words, but no deeds. So that we may cry to God with the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in his 12. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> for want of faithful dealing men; the <hi>Lord helpe vs, for they ſpeak euery one deceitfully with his neighbor, flattering with their lips, and ſpeake with a double heart.</hi> All this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, the rebellions of our Hieruſalem being ſo nye of kinne to Hieruſalems ſinne, may not God as iuſtly complaine of vs, as of Hieruſalem heere he doth? and may not he truely ſay to vs as to Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem? What, for all my mercies in that I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered you from Egypt, from Romes tyranny, and from the houſe of ſeruants, the ſlauery &amp; bondage of an vſurping <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the Pope? What, for all this, that I haue giuen you a <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>a Miriam,</hi> Kings and Queenes to be your nurſing Fathers, and nurſing Mothers, &amp; holy <hi>Aarons</hi> for your Paſtors? what, for al this, that I deliuerd you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euill in 88. was conſulted againſt you, when I turned Pope <hi>Balaams</hi> curſe into a bleſſing vnto you? what, for al this, that I daily ſend vnto you Voyces vpon Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20580:29"/>to cry and proclaime vnto your City what is the Lords will, and which is the way, that ye ſhould walke in it: for all theſe mercies of mine, for all this crying and preaching of my Voyces, <hi>adhucan ſunt?</hi> What, is it poſſible? Are there yet the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wickedneſſe in the houſe of the wicked? Are there yet ſcant meaſures, falſe balances, and a bagge of deceitfull weights in the ſhoppe of the wicked? Is there yet Violence and Oppreſſion in the heart of the wicked? And is there yet a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull tongue in the mouth of the wicked? If thus it bee, and you will not bee wonne by my mercies; if thus it bee, and you will not bee cured by my menaces; thou City of God, as to Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, ſo muſt I ſay to thee, though my beloued City; Yet thou ſhalt be puniſhed, and I will make thee as Hieruſalem, <hi>ſicke in ſmiting thee, becauſe of thy ſinnes, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore, thou beloued Citie of God, ſith God hath ſo bleſſed thee with his mercies, proue not thus vnkinde vnto thy God, do not ſo requite thy God for his mercies, as Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem did, but remoue with ſpeedy hand theſe thy ſinnes wherewith thou art charged from the Lord, and repent thee of the euill of thy ſinne, that God may repent him of the euill of puniſhment inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt thee for thy ſinne. Did not thy God loue thee, hee would not ſend thee Voyces vpon Voyces as he doth, to cry this in thine eares, that thou mayeſt preuent thy puniſhment by thy peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; and therefore if thou be wiſe, bee thou war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Hieruſalem, and auert Gods iudgements
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20580:29"/>from thee, by thy conuerſion to thy God. And in thy conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thou art to ſhake off Hieruſalems ſinne, and manifeſt rebellions, ſo haue not to doe with her ſaultring and ſecret hypocriſie in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerérſion: for Hieruſalem, as ſhe had her open re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, ſo had ſhe alſo her lurking hypocriſie; for doe but behold her, and ſee her hypocriſie in the ſixt verſe of this chapter: wheras if now ſhe meant to make a mends for all her rebellions, ſhee breakes forth in a ſtraine, pleaſing enough in the eare of man; but God, who ſees the heart, knew it to be but glozing and hypocriſie. (Oh) ſaith ſhe, <hi>in quo occurram,</hi> wherewith ſhall I come before the Lord? I will bring with mee my thouſands of Rammes, my tenne thouſand riuers of oyle. I will ſpare no coſt to appeaſe my God: nay, more then this; I will giue the fruit of my body for the ſinne of my ſoule: And what? not all this yet as much as God requires? No (O) man, God he requires not ſo much of thee: for in the eight verſe this onely is the thing the Lord requires; but <hi>to doe iuſtly, and to loue mercy, and to walke humbly with thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therfore, thou City of God, be thou farther inſtructed by Hieruſalem, and as thou art to leaue Hieruſalems ſinne, that thou mayſt eſcape Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalems puniſhment: So in thy conuerſion to thy God, play thou not the Hypocrite as Hieruſalem did. Bring we not then our thouſand Rams for an offering vnto God; but offer wee vp our ſelues, ſoule and body, a liuing ſacrifice vnto God.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> Bring we not our ten thouſand riuers of oyle; but bring
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20580:30"/>we with vs penitent hearts and eyes like holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids, to guſh out riuers of teares, becauſe we, none of vs keepe Gods Law.</hi> Bring we not the fruit of our body for the ſinne of our ſoule, but good workes the fruit of our faith, for the ſinne of our ſoule, the fruit of infidelity: and ſo doe wee that which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of vs; to doe iuſtly, to loue mercy, and to walke humbly with our God; for this is it which the Lords Voyce cryeth vnto the City, and let vs now ſeeke a man, a fit man, a man of wiſedome, to heare what the Voyce cryeth: <hi>For the man of wiſedome ſhall ſee thy name.</hi> It is eaſie to finde men, but it is hard to finde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a man: wee may goe vp and downe the City with <hi>Diogenes,</hi> &amp; finde thouſands of men, but not a man among a thouſand. It is eaſie to find <hi>Adam,</hi> a man of earth, it is eaſie to finde <hi>Enoſh,</hi> a man of infirmity; but to finde <hi>Iſh,</hi> a man of wiſedome and courage, this man is hard to finde; and yet no man is a fit man to heare the voyce of the Lord, but this man of wiſedome: and therefore wee muſt ſeeke narrowly for this man of wiſedome, whom we ſhall be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to diſcern, if we diſtinguiſh men into three rankes, and place in the firſt ranke, men of folly, in the ſecond, men of wiſedome, but with this reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>in ſuo genere,</hi> in their kind; in the third ranke, men of wiſedome indeed, men ſanctified from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, wiſe vnto ſaluation, who are the onely fit men to heare the voyce of the Lord. For the firſt, men of folly: There bee at this day in the world, two ſort of fooles, mad fooles, and golden fooles;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20580:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>and of the mad fooles holy <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaks in his 53. Pſalme, verſ. 1. <hi>The foole hath ſaid in his hart, There is no God:</hi> and doe but a while ſuruey the paſſages of his life, and you will ſay hee is a mad foole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; for he hath no other God but his belly, for his belly is his god:<note place="margin">Philip. 3.19.</note> &amp; neuer did thoſe fooliſh Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians in that ſtory, offer vp more daily to their Idol <hi>Bel,</hi> then he doth daily to his Idoll belly, to his god, his belly; his drinke-offerings are healths and carowſes; the Incenſe which hee burnes, Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſmoake: his Church, none but a Play-houſe: the ordinary ſermons which he hears, a Comedy: his funerall ſcrmons, a Tragedy: his Morning prayer, God damne mee: his Euening prayer, Deuill take body and ſoule. Now what a madde Bedlam is this, in ſuch madde humors, to ieſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his ſoule? But (O) that this man were wiſe, and would leaue this iouiall folly, to learne <hi>Iehouahs</hi> feare,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.10.</note> that the Angels in Heauen might reioyce at his conuerſion, as the Diuels in hell now laugh at his folly and deſtruction!</p>
            <p>Now the ſecond ſort of fooles are of <hi>Diues</hi> kin, who for all his riches,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.20.</note> is called in the Goſpell but a foole: and theſe fooles, they ſay to the wedge of gold, <hi>Thou art our God:</hi> and the ſeruice of their God is in <hi>conotouſneſſe, which is idolatry;</hi> ſo that they bee idolaters,<note place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> and delight in nothing more then in a maſſe, euen a maſſe of mony, which is all they care for; now preach to ſuch <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, preach profit to them, and they heare you gladly; but preach vnto them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, preach Chriſt vnto them, and they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20580:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>heare you not: Theſe, though they be not ſo mad, yet they be as bad fools as the former: for though they will not abuſe Gods bleſſings as the former, and empty their purſe vpon their belly, yet (which is almoſt as bad) they will not vſe Gods bleſſings at all, but empty their belly for their purſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the golden meane it is, which commends the man. And therefore the man of wiſdome, hee ſtands by, and ſees the folly of both theſe, and learnes the inſtruction of wiſdome by them both; ſo that hee is neither for the belly his god, nor yet for gold his god, but his onely requeſt to God, is that of the Wiſe-man in the thirtieth of Prouerbs, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> 
               <hi>Feed me (O Lord) with food conuenient for me.</hi> And thus now you ſee the madneſſe of folly: See wee withall in the ſecond place, the folly of ſome wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:<note place="margin">Iames 3.15.</note> There is a wiſdome which Saint <hi>Iames</hi> tells vs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>is not from aboue;</hi> but it is earthly, ſenſuall and diuelliſh. It is firſt earthly, it ſtudies only how to get lands and liuings on earth, it cares not at all for the Land of the liuing in Heauen: It is ſenſuall, all it mindes, is for the pleaſure of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it mindes not at all the comforts of the ſoule: It is diuelliſh,<note place="margin">2a. 2ae. Quaest. <hi>45.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Diabolica</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aquinas) propter imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperbiae Diaboli,</hi> Diuelliſh, becauſe it makes the man that hath it proud, and enuious as the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueil. Now this Diuelliſh wiſdome, it is in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels gift, and he hath beſtowed it on the proud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring Ieſuit, who by this Diuelliſh wiſdome, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triuing the death of Princes, and downefall of States and Kingdomes, vpholds the ſenſuall wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20580:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Prieſts in pleaſure, and the earthly wiſdome of the Pope in ſtate and magnificence: but farre be this wiſdome from vs, it makes vs <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientes,</hi> it makes vs wiſe,<note place="margin">Ierem. 4.22.</note> but (as ſaith the Prophet) <hi>wiſe onely to doe euill.</hi> And therefore take we heed of this wiſdome; for it is diuelliſh, it is from the Diuell, and it fits vs for the Diuell, making vs the Diuels Apes, by imitation of his practices in this life, and the Diuels Heires, by partaking of his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments in hell fire. And therefore againe and againe take we heed of this diuelliſh wiſdome, and let vs ſeeke for the true wiſdome, which S. <hi>Iames</hi> tels vs, <hi>is from aboue, from the Father of lights,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1.5. &amp; 6.</note> who giueth the true wiſdome to euery one that asketh of him, if hee aske in faith. Now this wiſdome, which <hi>is from God aboue,</hi> and which onely truely denominates a man, a man of wiſdome, hath two properties: For firſt, as <hi>Aquinas</hi> obſerues,<note place="margin">2a. 2ae. Quaeſt. <hi>45.</hi> Art. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; Art. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> it makes a man <hi>contemplari diuina,</hi> to fix his heart in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation vpon God. And then ſecondly it ſerues, <hi>regulare humanos actus,</hi> to regulate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our actions: For the firſt, the chiefe poynt of true wiſdome is in the firſt place, to haue an eye to God and to his Lawes; ſo that though wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with men on earth,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note> yet our conuerſation may be with God in heauen: and this we haue prooued vnto vs out of the 4. of Deut. verſ. 6. where (ſaith God) <hi>Keepe my Lawes and ordinances, and doe them:</hi> for, <hi>Haec eſt Sapientia, This is your wiſdome: and if ye thus obſerue and keep my ſtatutes, the people round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you ſhall ſay of you, Onely this people is wiſe, and of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20580:32"/>vnderſtanding, and a great nation.</hi> By this then ſhall you diſcerne a man of wiſdome, ſeeſt thou a man like <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> iuſt and walking in the ordinances of his God? Seeſt thou a man like vnto <hi>Cornelius,</hi> a deuout man, and one that feareth God? Seeſt thou a man like vnto <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> a true Iſraelite indeed, in whom there is no guile? Seeſt thou a man like vnto S. <hi>Paul,</hi> crucified to the world, and therefore held of the world but a foole for Chriſts ſake? Bee bold to ſay it, Such a man as this, and none but ſuch a man as this, is the man of wiſdome, of whom we ſpeake: For though the world be not ſo quick-ſighted, as to pierce into the depth of this; How this can bee, that a man who forſakes the pleaſures and vanities of the world, and liues in the world, dead to the world, as a man out of the world, whoſe conuerſation is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; that this man, hee ſhould bee the onely man of wiſdom in the world: Though (I ſay) the world doth not eaſily attain to the reach of this, yet may the world ſoone be brought to confeſſe this truth, by the euidence of her owne iudgement in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters: For the world deemes him the onely wiſe man, who is prouident for after-times, and who with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> can lay vp in time of plenty,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.33.</note> for the time of dearth: now who more prouident in this kind, then this man of wiſdom, of whom we ſpeak? who more laies vp for after-times then he? for he is ſtil conuerſant in Gods book, which is a rich ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe for the ſoule, to furniſh it with the Panoplie of a Chriſtian;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> and therefore hee ſtill hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20580:32"/>to this rich treaſurie, to furniſh his ſoule with all things needfull at all aſſayes for after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times; and in time of proſperitie, hee ſtores vp patience to help him in aduerſitie; in time of health, he ſtores vp Gods mercies to refreſh him in his ſickneſſe; in time of peace and quietneſſe, he ſtores vp conſtancie and Chriſtian reſolution, to back him out in time of perſecution. And as he is thus prouident for the good of his ſoule in this life; ſo is hee moſt of all prouident for his ſoules good after this life. For hee like a good Pilgrime-Traueller, becauſe hee would not cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his ſoule too much with the traſh of this world, which might hinder his expedition in his iourney to Heauen, hee wiſely ſends his treaſures to Heauen before him: ſome on poore mens backs, cloathing them; ſome in poore mens bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, feeding them; and ſome in poore mens hands, liberally relieuing them, to meete him in Heauen, when himſelfe comes thither, where his ſoule is ſure to finde them, and a reward with them.</p>
            <p>Now let the world ſpeake truth; whether this ſo prouident a man, bee not the onely man of wiſedome in the world. And I would to God all that haue ſoules to ſaue, would bee thus wiſe vnto ſaluation, and would bee as prouident for their ſoules, as they are carefull for their bodies, that wiſedome might imbrace vs all for her children.</p>
            <p>Now the ſecond propertie of true wiſedome is;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20580:33"/>it ſerues to regulate and rule out our actions, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them goe in a ſtraight and right line: for all our wayes are crooked wayes, till ſuch time as wiſedome make ſtraight ſteps vnto our feete: and therefore Wiſedome may well bee called the ſoules Controuler; and happy is the ſoule, where wiſedome is controuler. For Wiſedome or Folly is the Miſtreſſe of all our actions, and folly is to our actions, as the Varlet Baud is to the Strumpet, to entiſe vs vnto ſinne; but wiſedome is to our actions, as the naturall Mother to her child, to winne vs vnto goodneſſe. Folly ſaith to the yong heyre, Be prodigall now thou haſt it, and let it flie in vanitie: but ſaith Wiſedome vnto him, Liue honeſtly, now thou haſt it, and vſe it to ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie. Saith Folly to the old Man, Bee couetous now thou haſt it, and let it lye by thee. But ſaith Wiſedome vnto him, Doe good while thou haſt it, for therefore was it giuen thee. Folly, bids the angry man giue a ſtab for a wrong: but Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is for patience. Folly bids the ryotous man exceed in his Dyet: but Wiſedome is for Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance. Folly bids vs get it, no matter how: but Wiſedome is for conſcience. And thus doe Wiſedome and Folly ſtriue for our actions: and one while we yeeld to folly, and another while to wiſedome: but happy hee, who when hee ſees Wiſedome and Folly thus plead <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> for his actions, iudges wiſely of the matter, and giues Wiſedome but her due. For ſuch a man, hee is a man of wiſedome, a man in whom Wiſedome
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20580:33"/>delights: For the obedient eare, is wiſedomes delight: And therefore this man, hee is the onely fit man to heare Gods Voice; becauſe wiſedome makes him to ſee Gods Name, while hee ſtill beholds God in an holy contemplation, and ſtill drawes neerer and neerer vnto God, in an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly conuerſation. For <hi>the man of wiſedome ſhall ſee thy Name: Videbit nomen,</hi> Shall ſee thy name. One would take it at firſt bluſh, to bee more na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall in proprietie of ſpeech, for the Prophet to haue ſaid, Shall heare thy name, rather then Shall ſee thy name. But it is moſt ſignificant as it is, The man of wiſedome ſhall ſee thy name. For wee often heare Gods name, and we feare it not. For ſome, who heare it, blaſpheme it: and moſt, who heare it, regard it not with that reuerence, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemes the high Maieſtie of ſo great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a name. Whereas, did wee propoſe to our ſelues to ſee Gods name: did we ſee, and behold, with the eye of Faith, the holy Angels of Heauen ſtill praiſing this name: Did wee ſee and behold the Diuels in hell trembling at this name: Did wee ſee and behold the Saints on earth adoring this name: Did wee ſee and behold all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God obeying this name, our hearts would tremble within vs, to take this holy name into our mouth, but with feare and reuerence: we would feare vainely to ſweare by, and blaſpheme as wee doe, this holy name, which the Angels in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, with continuall. Halle-lu-iahs, praiſe &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie: and the Saints on earth, with all the deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20580:34"/>of an humbled foule reuerence and adore: and wee would euen quake and tremble, ſleightly, as too too commonly wee doe, vpon euery ſmall occaſion, to vſe this holy name, at which euen the Diuels themſelues doe tremble, and all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God ſtoope, and obey. And therefore, he that is a man of wiſedome amongſt vs, he will endeuour to ſee further then ordinarie; he will ſee Gods name: When he heares Gods name to be a name of Power; he will withall in the rare work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, and exquiſite fabricke of Heauen and earth, ſee and acknowledge the Maieſtie of this name: when he heares Gods name to be a name of glory and great renowne; he will withall, in the continuall praiſes of Saints and Angels, who day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſing <hi>Te Deums</hi> vnto God, ſee and acknowledge the glory of this name. To be briefe, hee that is a man of wiſedome amongſt vs, when hee heares Gods Name proclaimed in his Word; if this mooue him not, hee will ioyne his eyes vvith his eares, and ſee Gods name glorious in his works, which will ſtrike him with aſtoniſhment. For wee are all of vs like the Queene of <hi>Saba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 10.</note> readier to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue our eyes, then our eares: She heares of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> wiſedome; but ſhee credits not the report, till ſhee comes to be an eye-witneſſe of <hi>Salomons</hi> glory, when ſhee is greatly aſtonied to ſee his wiſedome, and the glory of his houſe: So wee, hearing of Gods wiſedome, his glory, and his power preached vnto vs in his Word: though our tongues confeſſe not ſo much to the world, yet
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20580:34"/>our hearts (ſuch is the imagination of the heart, onely euill, and that continually) oftentimes fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call in queſtion the truth of what we heare, and doubts ariſe whether all bee true: But when once with our eyes wee ſee Gods wiſedome, in the order and gouernance of his creatures, and his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and power in their excellency, we then beginne to ſtand aſtonied at the luſtre of ſo high a Maieſty. And this is it which holy <hi>Iob</hi> confeſſeth: <hi>I haue heard of thee by the hearing of the eare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 42.5, &amp; 6.</note> 
               <hi>but now mine eye ſeeth thee, I abhorre my ſelfe, and repent in dust &amp; aſhes.</hi> And therefore againe and againe let mee vrge it to you, as you deſire to approue your ſelues men of wiſedome; haue this property of a wiſe man in you, to haue your eyes ſtill in your head, ready vpon all aſſaies to ſee Gods name. And in your proſperity, ſee Gods gracious name, to praiſe him for his bounty; in your aduerſity, ſee Gods powerfull name, to call vpon him for his helpe and mercy: ſee his name, a tower to defend you in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: ſee his name, a ſweet oyntment to refreſh you in ſickneſſe: ſee his name, a Sauiour to ſaue you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſins, that ye deſpaire not of mercy: and ſee his name, a Iudge to queſtion you for you ſinnes, that you preſume not of mercy. To be briefe, ſet God alwaies before your eyes, and in all your actions ſee Gods name; in the beginning, to begin in the feare of his name, and ſee Gods name in the ending to conclude to the glory of his name, that your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being begun, continued, and ended in him, they may be crowned and accepted of him.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:20580:35"/>
            <p> Thus, would we ſtill but ſee Gods name for the direction of our actions, wee ſhould not neede to feare Gods rodde wherewith he puniſhes the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of our actions: but becauſe wee often, more for faſhions ſake then any true deuotion, preſſe to this and ſuch like places; onely to heare Gods name, and yet prooue little better, becauſe withall wee doe not propoſe vnto our ſelues to ſee Gods name, to feare Gods name, we, who will not vſe our eyes to ſee Gods name, for this contempt are heere ſummoned by the Prophet to vſe our eares, and to heare Gods rod: <hi>Heare ye the rod, and who hath appointed it:</hi> of which but in a word.</p>
            <p>It is not beare ye the rodde, but onely <hi>audite,</hi> heare ye the rod: ſo that if ye heare the rodde, and preuent the ſtroke with penitence and teares, with faſtings and with prayers, and all the true deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an humbled ſoule, it is in your owne choice whether or no ye feele the rod: For Niniueh that great City, when ſhee no ſooner heard the rodde, <hi>Yet forty daies, and Niniueh ſhall be destroyed,</hi> but from the higheſt to the loweſt,<note place="margin">Ionah 3.</note> they humbled themſelues in ſackcloth, and in aſhes. This humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation of theirs, their faſting, their ſackcloth, and their aſhes, were as ſo many Orators to pleade for mercy for them in the eares of God, and God ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the City, and heard their cry: becauſe they firſt heard the cry of his Voyce, <hi>Yet forty daies, and Niniuch ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> and ſtraight vpon it humbled themſelues in duſt and aſhes. Now God, he cries the ſame in the eares of this City, as hee
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20580:35"/>did to <hi>Niniueh, audite,</hi> heare ye the rod: and if ye now heare the rod as <hi>Niniueh</hi> did, &amp; humble your ſelues with faſtings and with prayers, nor onely ſo, but which is moſt memorable in <hi>Niniuchs</hi> humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, as it is recorded in the 3. of <hi>Ionah, v.</hi> 8. If eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man turne from the euill of his way, ſome from their ſwearing, ſome from their carowſing, ſome from their oppreſſing, all from their euill dealing: thou beloued City of God, vpon this thy humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the rod ſhall much rather depart from thee, then it did from <hi>Niniueh:</hi> onely <hi>audite,</hi> heare ye on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ye men of Iſrael, and <hi>waſh thee, O Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 4. v. 14.</note> 
               <hi>from thy wickedneſſe, that thou maiſt be ſaued.</hi> Now as the comfort is, the rod, it comes not ſodainly and vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares vpon vs, but with an <hi>audite,</hi> firſt heare yee it, which is as the word of peace offered to a Nation, before the ſword be once vnſheathed for the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell. So the comfort alſo is, that it is but <hi>virga,</hi> it is but a rod, it is not the <hi>axe</hi> in the 3. of <hi>Math. laid to the root of the tree,</hi> quite to cut downe <hi>euery tree that bringeth not forth good fruit.</hi> It is not <hi>virga ferrea,</hi> Gods <hi>iron rod</hi> in the 2. <hi>Pſalm. to cruſh and breake in pieces</hi> theſe bodies of earth, <hi>like a Potters veſſel:</hi> but it is onely <hi>virga,</hi> it is onely but a rod; and as the comfort is, that it is onely but a rod, ſo the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort alſo is, that it is <hi>a Deo,</hi> it is from God, God hath appointed it, who is our Father, to be a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle correction for his children.</p>
            <p>But let not now theſe comforts make vs care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of the iudgement, and becauſe God is ſlow to anger, and doth not ſtraight puniſh, but often firſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20580:36"/>call vpon vs for repentance, Heare ye the rod, &amp; ſo amend: Let vs not wilfully miſtake Gods mercy, and vpon this bee ſlow in our conuerſion vnto God, becauſe the puniſhment, when it comes, it is but a rod; let not vs ſlight the puniſhment, and ſeem careleſſe of the iudgement, becauſe the rod, when it is vpon vs, it is in a Fathers hand, who is moſt tender in his puniſhments; let not this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage vs in our ſins, for though the rod be from God a Father, yet is it alſo from God a moſt ſeuere Iudge, though the rod come with an <hi>Audite,</hi> Heare yee it, and make delay? Why, the more delayes bee in the ſtroke, the more heauy is the ſtroke, and payes the homer when it comes: though the rod when it comes, be but a rod, yet a rod it is, and ſuch a rod, which makes the whole world our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; for the whole world, it is Gods rod, wherwith he ſcourges the rebellious nation. The fire, it was Gods rod, to conſume the two Captaines of the King of Samaria and their followers, who came violently to ſurprize the Lords Prophet.<note place="margin">2. Reg. 1.</note> The earth,<note place="margin">Numb. 16.</note> it was Gods rod, to ſwallow vp <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> for their rebellion: The water, it was Gods rod, to drowne the old world, and to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the hoſt of <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> And, for a long while, the infected aire hath beene a rod vnto this City. Warre, it is Gods rod, to puniſh the vnthankfull abuſe of peace: Famin, it is Gods rod to puniſh the vnthankfull abuſe of his creatures: Peſtilence, it is Gods rod, wherewith, for a long time, God hath puniſhed this City, and now hee doth but ſtrike a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20580:36"/>ſtroke or two with this rod, take away ſome one or two with his heauy plague; and that not often neither, but now and then, to ſee if this his gentle correction will make vs wiſe; now at laſt men of wiſdome, to ſee his name, heare his rod, and feare his Maieſty, that the euill come not vpon vs for our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And thus now you ſee, though it be but a rod which is heere menaced againſt vs, yet in that it is a rod, it is enough to ſet heauen and earth againſt vs: and therefore ſith it is ſo, that euery creature of God, at the great Makers command, is a rod rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at hand, to ſcourge the rebellious nation, this ſhould teach vs to liue in an awfull feare of this rod, and when Satan tempts vs to ſinne, to looke about vs, and thinke euery creature we ſee, an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to vs, if wee ſinne; for this will make vs ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vnto ſinne. Haue we then (if we be wiſe) ſtill an eye to this rod, and ſo learne we to feare God, in whoſe hand it is, that while we liue in feare of God and of his rod, God may not feare vs with his rod: For, as for vs (Beloued) wee feare what our ſinnes deſerue, there is ſome rod, ſome iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or other houering ouer our heads: but let vs in time preuent the Iudgement, and heare the Lords Voyce from Heauen. Now hee doth premoniſh vs, that hee may take his rod from vs, and not puniſh vs, let vs come before God with tears in our eies, with <hi>Peccaui</hi> in our mouthes, with deuotion in our hearts, and with almes in our hands; that God ſeeing our penitence, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20580:37"/>his puniſhments. It is an vſuall ſaying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, Euery good childe, he will go vnto his father, and keep his Mid-lent with his father. And let vs heerein approue our ſelues good children in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of God our heauenly Father, in going this day vnto him our Father, euery one of vs, who are ſo many Prodigals of Gods graces and mercies towards vs, following the good reſolution of the Prodigall:<note place="margin">Luke 15.18.</note> goe we <hi>vnto our Father, and ſay vnto Him; Father, wee haue ſinned againſt Heauen and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Thee, and are no more worthy to bee called thy ſonnes:</hi> Accept vs, Holy Father, we beſeech thee, and imbrace vs with the armes of thy mercy, now we come vnto thee: ſpare thy people, who turne vnto thee with faſtings and with prayers, and all the true deuotions of an humbled and ſanctified ſoule, and take thy rod from vs; for we will heare thy Voyce to obey it, and ſee thy name, to feare it and to praiſe it: Onely open our eyes, that we may ſee; and our eares, that wee may heare; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, <hi>Open thou our mouthes, that our lips may ſpeake thy praiſes:</hi> and ſo will we daily confeſſe, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of thy Name, vnto him that loued vs, and waſhed vs from our ſinnes in his owne bloud, and hath made vs Kings and Prieſts to God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 1.</note> 
               <hi>that faithfull Witneſſe, the firſt Begotten of the dead, and prince of the Kings of the earth; vnto Him,</hi> and vnto Him alone, for the riches of his mercy vnto vs, be all glory and praiſe, from this time forth, and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20580:38"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20580:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:20580:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:20580:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:20580:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20580:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20580:41"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20580:41"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20580:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:20580:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20580:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20580:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:20580:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20580:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20580:45"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20580:45"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20580:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20580:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:20580:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20580:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:20580:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:20580:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20580:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20580:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:20580:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20580:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20580:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20580:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20580:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20580:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
